<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact and true narrative of the late popish intrigue, to form a plot, and then to cast the guilt and odium thereof upon the Protestants ... faithfully collected by Col. Roderick Mansell.</title>
            <author>Mansell, R. (Roderick)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20941</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12047454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12047454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 870:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact and true narrative of the late popish intrigue, to form a plot, and then to cast the guilt and odium thereof upon the Protestants ... faithfully collected by Col. Roderick Mansell.</title>
                  <author>Mansell, R. (Roderick)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 105 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Cockerill and Benj. Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:53111:1"/>
            <p>I Do Appoint <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> and <hi>Benjamin Alſop</hi> to Print this Narrative, and that no other Print the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RODERICK MANSELL.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. 17. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Exact and True NARRATIVE OF THE LATE Popiſh Intrigue, TO FORM A PLOT, And then To caſt the GUILT and ODIUM thereof UPON THE PROTESTANTS. Wherein are contained,
<list>
                  <item>I. The Contrivance it ſelf, with the <hi>Principal Agents</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> viz. The Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>II. The manner of carrying on the ſaid Contrivance,</item>
                  <item>III. The Continuance of the Popiſh Plot to Aſſaſſinate the KING.</item>
                  <item>IV. The Book found in the Houſe of Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> in a Meal-Tub, by Sir <hi>William Waller.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. The ſeveral Attempts to Murther the Right Honourable, <hi>Anthony</hi> Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VI. The manner of Conveying a Liſt of Names and other Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Papers, into the Chamber of Col. <hi>Roderick Manſell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VII. The full Examination of the whole Affair before the Lords of His Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Council. With the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification of divers Informations, Examinations, Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> relating to the ſaid Intrigue.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Collected by Col. <hi>RODERICK MANSELL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Cockerill</hi> and <hi>Benj. Alſop,</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs,</hi> and at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53111:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53111:2"/>
            <head>A Solemn ADDRESS TO All true ENGLISH PROTESTANTS, BY Col. <hi>RODERICK MANSELL.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured, and Worthy Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat accurſed Deſigns have <hi>formerly</hi> been ſet on foot to undermine, and blow up the <hi>Religion,</hi> that is, <hi>The true intereſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> your <hi>own Concerns</hi> therein have made you too apprehenſive to need a <hi>Remembrancer;</hi> and that your Enemies are <hi>no Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> but as <hi>unwearied</hi> as <hi>pregnant</hi> (and, thanks be to God, as <hi>unſucceſsful</hi>) in their malicious Contrivances as ever; had you no Friends, they themſelves will do you that <hi>one and only</hi> friendly Office, to become your <hi>faithful Monitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some have obſerv'd, that <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a thouſand various ſhapes, and yet under all thoſe Diſguiſes, <hi>Mercury,</hi> will be <hi>Mercury;</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> a <hi>Devil;</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite;</hi> when he ceaſes <hi>to Be,</hi> he may ceaſe to <hi>be miſchievous;</hi> and when he puts off <hi>his Eſſence,</hi> may poſſibly put off <hi>his pragmaticalneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all their <hi>other Plots,</hi> they have <hi>out-done the World;</hi> in this laſt tryal of their skill, they have <hi>out-done</hi> (and we hope <hi>undone</hi>) <hi>themſelves;</hi> for 'tis a Queſtion, (and muſt remain ſo, for any ſolution of mine) whether their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in contriving;</hi> their <hi>Activity in purſuing;</hi> their <hi>Impudence in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> their Fruitleſs Attempts for corrupting the Evidence; or this their laſt Eſſay, to devolve the <hi>Odium,</hi> of their execrable Treaſon againſt the King and Kingdom, upon the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> have been more (though all have been beyond example) Devilliſh.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge this is no modern Artifice, nor the Invention of junior Heads, their Anceſtors have travelled in the ſame Argument, wrought in the ſame Mine; for when they had formed the <hi>Powder-Plot,</hi> they conſulted to lay the Baſtard at the <hi>Puritans</hi> Door; and what they had the pleaſure to <hi>beget,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers muſt have the reproach to <hi>Father;</hi> though the <hi>Deformed Brat,</hi> to all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning eyes, would apparently own its Sire.</p>
            <p>Now although in laying the ground-work of their late Project, they had a <hi>confuſed Idea,</hi> or <hi>rude draught</hi> of that Ancient Policy, yet could they not lick that unformed lump into a perfect ſhape, till time had ripened and ſharpened their Inventions. Mr. <hi>Dugdale,</hi> in his Evidence againſt Mr. <hi>Whitebread,</hi> and his Accomplices, (pag. 25.) ſwears, <hi>That a Letter came from</hi> Paris, <hi>through Mr.</hi> Harcourt<hi>'s hands into the Country, to prove, That it was the Opinion of them at</hi> Paris <hi>and St.</hi> Omers, <hi>to fling all this upon the</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, <hi>that is,</hi> The death of the King, <hi>that if any thing of this nature ſhould happen, they ſhould be ready to give the firſt Allarm, and give it out that it <pb facs="tcp:53111:3"/>was the</hi> Still-King-killing Presbyterians <hi>that had done the Fact, and ſo they thought they ſhould bring the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>into their company, to revenge themſelves of the</hi> Presbyterians; to which the <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> replyed, <hi>It was pretty Advice indeed, to have it firſt laid on the</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>that they might get the</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>to joyn and cut their Throats, and then</hi> their own <hi>Throats ſhould be cut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe it was impoſſible, and therefore incredible, that ever <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould ſo groſly miſtake their Intereſt, as to conſpire the deſtruction of their King, who is the <hi>Center and Head</hi> of it; they had been long preparing the People to entertain the belief of it, againſt that happy juncture of time, which ſhould invite them openly to aſſert it; for theſe <hi>Theologico-Political Quacks,</hi> knew well that ſo great a Doſe of Improbabilities would work too rigidly upon the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> without due Preparatives to mittigate its ſurly Operation; and therefore, ſome good while before, they had been ſlily inſinuating into the credulous Brains of thoſe whom either ſimplicity, or a bad Intereſt, had made capable of ſuch Impreſſions, <hi>That the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>were a dangerous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men;</hi> that <hi>their Principles and Practices were inconſiſtent with Government, but carried a ſpecifick malignity againſt Monarchy;</hi> that <hi>they were certainly a brewing ſome deſperate miſchief, which a little time would diſcover;</hi> (and they could have told us the time to an hour.) That <hi>whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were tolerated, the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>were intolerable! and ſtill with great Zeal they reminded us of</hi> forty one, <hi>that we might not dream of</hi> ſeventy nine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marchemont Needham,</hi> in his Scurrulous <hi>Advice to the men of</hi> Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury; the Author of <hi>the Countermine;</hi> and <hi>R. L'Eſtrange,</hi> in their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Burleſques, always bore hard and down-right upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> but what is more remarkable, <hi>a day or two</hi> before the attempt to faſten this ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Treaſon upon my ſelf, the World was ſaluted with a Pamphlet, under the name of <hi>Tom. the Joyner,</hi> wherein we are gravely adviſed to <hi>come out from amongſt them</hi> (the Presbyterians) <hi>and not to partake of their Sins, leſt we received of their Plagues, which God had prepared for them;</hi> for they were conſcious to themſelves what Plagues <hi>they had prepared</hi> for them; and 'tis but the priviledge of their great Familiarity with God to make him eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe their Quarrels, and employ his Thunder according to the direction of the Conſult; but he goes on, That <hi>we ſhould not fear their Power, it would be but a</hi> Summers Storm; <hi>but e're long</hi> (within <hi>two days,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Dangerfield's</hi> Flint was but well fixed) <hi>their turn of ſuffering would come about; for God would make their Hearts to melt, and their Loyns to tremble;</hi> and for his part, he could be content <hi>his life were given in Sacrifice, that the King and his good Subjects might be preſerved from the moſt Damnable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock</hi> John Presbyter <hi>deſign'd to make amongſt us;</hi> but was it not eaſie to tell the World what the <hi>Presbyterians would do,</hi> when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had form'd for them a piece of Villany, which they <hi>muſt do,</hi> whether they <hi>would,</hi> whether they <hi>knew it or no?</hi> The Devil can certainly prognoſticate thoſe Plagues, which he has Commiſſion or Permiſſion to execute; and the Pope is not more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible in his <hi>Determinations de fide,</hi> than <hi>John Gadbury</hi> in his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions de facto,</hi> when he's a part of the Confederacy, and privy to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue.</p>
            <p>Yet though theſe Pamphlets (which were only the <hi>Title-Page</hi> to the Plot) ſuggeſted danger only from the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> Providence having unſealed and opened the <hi>Book it ſelf,</hi> we read there that the <hi>main Body of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:53111:3"/>were to be involv'd in the deſign: They had preferred the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Earls of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Radnor,</hi> the Lord <hi>Hallifax,</hi> all Members of His Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy Council, to be Counſellours in this their feigned Rebellion; nay they had introduced the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> and re-introduced his Grace the Duke of <hi>Bucks,</hi> and the right honourable the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury</hi> into the Plot; they had Commiſſioned the <hi>Lord Gray,</hi> the <hi>Lord Gerrard</hi> and his Son, and Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> to be <hi>Lieutenant Generals;</hi> but above all, his Grace the <hi>Duke of Monmouth</hi> was moſt beholden to them, whom, to compenſate the loſs of his General-ſhip over an Army of real men on <hi>Earth,</hi> they had now created <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> over an aiery Army of their own liſting, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered in the <hi>Clouds;</hi> and that they might not ſeem ridiculouſly contradictory to themſelves, to pretend <hi>a Presbyterian Plot,</hi> without <hi>one Presbyterian</hi> in it, they had graciouſly given a Commiſſion for <hi>Major-General</hi> to Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and ſprinkled here and there a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> like a Train to the Trap, and ſo from the <hi>leſs part,</hi> and almoſt <hi>no part,</hi> had denominated (by Jeſuits Logick) <hi>the whole to be Presbyterian,</hi> which gave occaſion to an ingenious Clergy-man to ſay, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Dangerfield <hi>had made more</hi> Presbyterians <hi>in a day, than they withal their Conventicles and preaching could make in twenty years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>ſtated Maxime,</hi> That <hi>Intereſt will not lye:</hi> No man in his wits would cut down that <hi>Bough of the Tree</hi> upon which <hi>he ſtands;</hi> nor ſhear aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>ſingle Cord</hi> upon which <hi>he hangs.</hi> How then is it credible that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> ſhould conſpire to take away <hi>that life by which they live?</hi> Can they be ſo vain as to promiſe themſelves fairer Quarter under <hi>any Succeſſor whom the Laws favour,</hi> than under the <hi>Auſpices</hi> of his Majeſty? When the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined fates of both are ſo interwoven, that they muſt <hi>weep and laugh, live and dye together:</hi> but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have drawn <hi>a Proteſtants face</hi> by <hi>a Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites heart,</hi> and whatever of <hi>Devilliſm</hi> they find in their own breaſts, fancy it to be lodged in other mens brains.</p>
            <p>I cannot but admire too, at the imprudence of ſome, who <hi>ſeem to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> (and of <hi>thoſe ſome,</hi> ſome are, I hope, <hi>really ſuch</hi>) that underſtand their <hi>own Intereſt</hi> no better, than to joyn with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> if not <hi>directly in their Counſels,</hi> yet <hi>obliquely in their Actions,</hi> to ruine any who are firm to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt; pleaſing themſelves that they ſhall deliver up Diſſenters to the <hi>Romiſh Polyphemus,</hi> when their only priviledge muſt prove to become <hi>the laſt</hi> (if the laſt) <hi>Morſel.</hi> Nor could I ever yet diſcern the Truth or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of that Charge, which loud Clamour has drawn up againſt thoſe who bear <hi>the name of Presbyterians;</hi> that <hi>they are Enemies to Monarchy.</hi> I have read that about threeſcore of them have <hi>openly proteſted againſt the Tryal and Execution of the late King,</hi> when ſome others were then ſilent, who are moſt clamorous: That they refuſed <hi>the Engagement whereby the Royal Family was renounced,</hi> when yet others ſwallowed it; that many of them <hi>were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred for their Loyalty,</hi> when ſome others enjoyed conſiderable Benefices: That ſome of them <hi>were Impriſoned, Executed,</hi> for adhereing to his preſent Majeſty's Intereſt, when others declined it; and that <hi>a conſiderable Army of that Perſwaſion</hi> aſſerted his Majeſty's Right with their Swords and Lives in their hands, when of the numerous Zealous Royaliſts ſcarce <hi>three hundred in the three Kingdoms</hi> appeared to joyn them: How forward they were with the formoſt, and actively inſtrumental in the reſtoration of His Majeſty to his Crown and Throne, the World remembers, and his Majeſty has not forgotten; and how they have ever ſince demeaned themſelves without any ſpot of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty <pb facs="tcp:53111:4"/>that could juſtly be fixt upon them, is ſo well known, that their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can ſooner envy it, than deny it: Nor can I perceive that they have repented of their Loyalty, though ſome have order'd matters ſo to tempt them to it. They have fallen under the ſeverities of the penal Laws, even thoſe made againſt Papiſts, and yet haue ſuffer'd with as much chearfulneſs, as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'twas poſſible for fleſh and blood to do: And that they ſhould be brought under a ſuſpicion of hatching Treaſonable deſignes, had been utterly unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that the Diſcovery of this late horrid Contrivance has convinced me, that the Maſter-piece of Papal policy lies here, <hi>To forge a falſe Plot againſt them, that they might conceal a real one of their own;</hi> and then to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the credulous world, that <hi>the Proteſtants</hi> had forged an Imaginary Plot for the Papiſts, <hi>laſt year,</hi> that they might hide that which they had deſigned to execute this <hi>preſent year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which helliſh Intrigue though I cannot tell whether there was a greater Mixture of <hi>Policy, or folly;</hi> yet this is evident, there was <hi>a great Mixture of both,</hi> of which, with your Patience (Gentlemen) I will now give you ſome ſhort Account, that you may have <hi>a through light into this work of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I. The Policy of the Papiſts in contriving this preſent horrid Plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Papiſts finding the Sword of Juſtice (which ſo long had ſlumber'd in the Scabbard) drawn againſt them for their Devilliſh Treaſon, judg'd it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to divert the edge another way; if therefore they could bring the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> under a ſuſpicion of that guilt whereof they ſtood clearly convicted, 'twas hoped the Current of the peoples fury, together with the juſt indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Magiſtrate, would turn alſo, and not run ſo violently againſt their Party; for all men naturally fortifie againſt <hi>the preſent evil,</hi> and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the <hi>lateſt, and freſheſt Enemy;</hi> and therefore it could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fall out, but that they muſt eaſe their own Shoulders, whileſt they loaded other mens Backs; and the Fire which threatned to burn them up, would ſlake, when they had provided it other Fewel: Their <hi>former Treaſons</hi> would be buried in the Grave of new <hi>Proteſtant Rebellions;</hi> and freſh Crimes would be a kind of <hi>an Act of Oblivion</hi> for their State-Villanies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They promis'd themſelves, that if their Plot had made thoſe Impreſſions upon his Majeſties belief, as to look upon <hi>ſo conſiderable a number of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects as Enemies to his Perſon, and Government,</hi> they ſhould then be the only <hi>White-boyes,</hi> and immediately jump into the Embraces of his Royal Arms: for what other Conſequences could follow from thoſe Premiſes? If the Proteſtants loſe ground, they muſt win it, and pitch their conquering Tents upon the deſerted Field.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt be Infinite ſatisfaction to their Revengeful Spirits, could they once ſee the moſt Eminent Proteſtants drawn to <hi>Tyburn</hi> in the ſame pompous State, wherein <hi>their Reverend Fathers, and glorious Martyrs,</hi> ſo lately rode thither; nor could any thing be ſweeter to ſuch a heightned Malice, than to ſee thoſe who had been their <hi>juſt Accuſers</hi> for Treaſon, to ſuffer, <hi>however innocently,</hi> for the ſame pretended Crimes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though their whole deſign be now laid open; yet may they hope for this conſiderable advantage, that now the Nation may be tempted to think, <hi>the late Popiſh Plot was but a Contrivance of the Proteſtants:</hi> ſince it evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that <hi>the preſent pretended Plot of the Proteſtants, is but a contrivance <pb facs="tcp:53111:4"/>of the Papiſts;</hi> Thus they would uſe their own <hi>notorious Lyes</hi> to perſwade us there is <hi>no Truth;</hi> and that all the world are Knaves, becauſe they have given us ſuch demonſtration of their Rogueries.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men indeed deſpiſe theſe reaſonings, but the far greater part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is none of the wiſeſt: and the Game is worth the Candle, if they can but captivate the belief of the many, who may prove good tools, though errant Fools: The <hi>Catholick Plot</hi> was apparently to their advantage, but this feigned one, had it really been, and been effectual, had ruined the Contrivers: Every man is ſuppos'd the Author of thoſe Counſels, by which he reaps benefit, hut there could be no temptation to <hi>the Proteſtants,</hi> to remove a <hi>Proteſtant Prince,</hi> to make room <hi>for one that is otherwiſe minded:</hi> The <hi>real Popiſh Plot,</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by ſuch a harmony of concurrent Circumſtances, ſuch a cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, who from all parts without knowledge of each others teſtimony, fell in with admirable proportion to the ſame thing, when this <hi>new Romance</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſelf conſiſtency, nor agreement with the Truth; And laſtly, the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> was diſcover'd by thoſe that had <hi>a hand, a head, a heart,</hi> in it, and were <hi>a great part of it,</hi> but this <hi>upſtart Forgery</hi> never was owned by any Proteſtant, and the very Authors, and main Engineers therein, haled by a guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, are come in to juſtifie us, and condemn themſelves of unpardonable wickedneſs and folly; which leads me to the ſecond thing I promiſed to diſcourſe of, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II. The notorious folly of the preſent Popiſh Figment deſigned to be laid upon the Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I profeſs I was ſomewhile inclined to think that the refined ſublimated Wits of the Jeſuits (who were never yet blamed for bungling at Miſchief,) could not poſſibly be the Authors of ſo dull a contrivance; but that ſome <hi>Flegmatick Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars,</hi> or heavy headed Bigots of the Laity, had the hammering of it: But we have had ſome pregnant inſtances, of the wiſeſt Counſels, which by ill ſucceſs have been chalkt o'th' back for Follies: For malice ſends ſuch thick fumes into the head, as often diſturb the underſtanding; great haſte makes the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt ſtumble, to which if we add the conſideration of the Divine Juſtice, whoſe glory it is to <hi>ſnare the wicked in the works of their own hands,</hi> it will go far to aſſoil the difficulty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Heterogeneous mixture</hi> of the perſons, joyned, or rather jumbled, together in one Conſpiracy, ſpeaks it's ill Contrivance: The Papiſts, I confeſs, have one ſingular advantage above all other men for a cleaver piece of Villany, in that they can be <hi>all of a piece</hi> in forming, and executing any deſign for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting their common cauſe, and oppoſing their common Enemies, for though they quarrel bitterly amongſt themſelves, the <hi>Dominicans</hi> hating, and hated by the <hi>Franciſcans:</hi> The <hi>Moliniſts</hi> perſecuting the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> and theſe again undermining thoſe; yet they all conſpire in advancing that unweildy Kingdom, whereof the Pope is the Head; whereas the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> having <hi>no other point,</hi> wherein they can politically unite, but in the Perſon, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Sacred Majeſty; if once you ſuppoſe them <hi>to divide in that Center,</hi> they muſt divide <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and can never meet in <hi>any Third.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Twas but a raw project, to Introduce as diſcerning and apprehenſive Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as the Nation, perhaps as the world, can boaſt of, ſo ſilly as to engage in a work which muſt inevitably involve them in deſtruction: Either their Plot would ſucceed, or not: If it miſcarries, <hi>the Law</hi> deſtroys them; If it ſucceeds, <hi>their Enemies</hi> deſtroy them; for I doubt not to avow to all the World; that <pb facs="tcp:53111:5"/>ſome of the moſt conſiderable perſons, whom theſe <hi>Plot-makers</hi> had aſſign'd to dig in the Mine, muſt with all their concerns be blown up, to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, as ſoon as ever the Mine was ſprung: Who ſees not that many of them hold their Eſtates, Honours, Dignities, Offices, Preferments, yea Liberties and Lives, for Term at longeſt, of his Majeſty's life and Throne; ſo that to feign them his Aſſaſſinates, is but to ſuppoſe them <hi>ſelf-murderers;</hi> and were they in Chains in a Dungeon, yet ſo far as life is deſirable they are bound in their own defence to make it a ſtanding Petition in their Oriſons, <hi>God preſerve the King of</hi> Great-Brittain.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Twas but odly laid, to aſſign the Cabals and Clubs, for forming and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageing this hair-brain'd Plot, to publick houſes, <hi>The Kings-head-Tavern, the Sun-Tavern, the Green-Dragon-Tavern,</hi> and a Chandlers Shop in <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> where to be ſure (if any were) all the Knavery muſt <hi>come to light;</hi> that they ſhould meet in common Rooms, the through-fares for the Family, at ſtated days, fixed hours, with a mixed multitude, of various Intereſts, Humours, Tempers, and Inclinations, who could not poſſibly underſtand each others propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, nor how the pulſe of their Affections beat; where without precaution any might be admitted, and the Trapans were admitted, and all this to expedite a Project ſo dangerous to themſelves, ſo damnable in it ſelf, ſo improbable to ſucceed; this is it which poſes my belief, and ſtrands the faith of any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thinking perſon.</p>
            <p>Obſerve but with what Circumſpection the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> convene in their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults;</hi> how ſhy and cautelous they are of their own Friends, who are not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally engaged in the Confederacy: that famous Letter found amongſt <hi>Harcourt's</hi> Papers, produced in the Tryals of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Whitebread,</hi> might have taught us ſome Policy, had we needed their fineſſes to ſubſerve any vile occaſions of our own.—<hi>Every one is minded alſo not to haſten to</hi> London long before the time appointed, nor to appear much about the Town till the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be over, leſt occaſion be given to ſuſpect the deſign: Finally, Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as to time and place, is recommended to all thoſe that receive Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as it will appear in its own nature neceſſary. Surely theſe grand States-men might have ſuppoſed us to have ſome ſmall pittance of Brains, and not to engroſs all the Subtlety, as they have monopoliz'd the Knavery, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: They that were ſo timorous, even to Superſtition, in their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, might have allow'd us common ſenſe, and not have repreſented us <hi>in a Plot,</hi> as they have done ſome Religious Perſons <hi>in a Play,</hi> for a company of crack-brain'd, non-ſenſical fools; and I aſſure them, were I capable of a provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to bring <hi>an Action of ſlander</hi> againſt them, I would lay it, not only for perſonating me as <hi>a Traytor,</hi> but <hi>a Coxcomb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The manner of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> and his <hi>Privadoes,</hi> faſtening this Plot upon my ſelf, ſpeaks notorious folly; he tells <hi>Capt. Bedford</hi> that his friend for whom he had taken the Lodging was <hi>not yet come to Town,</hi> and yet he tells Mrs. <hi>Harris</hi> before <hi>Bedford,</hi> that this <hi>Capt. Bedford</hi> was <hi>that Friend for whom he had taken it;</hi> he informs the Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe, that there were Contreband Goods to the value of 2000 <abbr>l.</abbr> ſtowed in my Chamber, and yet was ſollicitous to remove me <hi>one pair of Staires higher.</hi> Now how inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent this was with a ſuppoſition that I had ſuch a quantity of Goods in my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, is obvious: for what a noiſe muſt we have had with Joyners to contrive new Cells, Drawers, Cloſets, Lockers, to conceal them? What an over-ſight was it to direct the Searchers to look behind the Beds-head, before he had lodged his Papers there; had he been his Crafts-maſter, he ſhould firſt have depoſited <pb facs="tcp:53111:5"/>the Treaſon, and then have left the Officers to remove the Bed; which their Zeal, hot in purſuit of a Prize, would infallibly have adviſed them too; what Foolery was it to cry out <hi>Treaſon,</hi> before he had read more than the uſual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to a Letter? I do really believe, the <hi>Devil and his Jeſuites</hi> never ſent a more ſimple Child on their Errands! and what madneſs was it, to inform of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited or uncuſtomed Goods, when he knew there were none ſuch there? and to make that the umbrage to ſearch for Treaſon, which he as little knew to be there, ſeeing the tracing him a Lyar in one inſtance, might have raiſed ſome duſt of ſuſpicion in the Spectators Eyes, that indeed all the reſt was but a great For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery?</p>
            <p>And yet the ſame wretched Impolitickneſs have they uſed in their other Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, When <hi>Hettervile's</hi> deſign to Corrupt honeſt <hi>Capt. Berry,</hi> proved abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, they are preſently at work again with <hi>Capt. Bedlow;</hi> and when <hi>Reading</hi> was ſo handſomly over-reacht, yet they are incapable of fair warning, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the ſame threed-bare Method with <hi>Dr. Oates.</hi> And when that pitiful project proved unſucceſsful; they proceed in the ſame dull, baffled track with <hi>Mr. Dugdale:</hi> and when they have caſt up the accounts of theſe particulars, the total is thus much, <hi>a real proof of their true Plot,</hi> and their infatuation in the Conduct of this falſe one: And ſtill they proceed with that Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as if they were abſolute Maſters of all Events, and could Command ſucceſs to wait upon their Stirrup, whatever Idle means they uſe, or in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Improper Methods they proceed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor does it argue more of Wiſdom, to rear ſuch <hi>a Maſſive Tow'ring Structure</hi> as that of <hi>a Plot, againſt his Majeſties Perſon and Government,</hi> upon ſo <hi>ſlender and ſleighty a Foundation;</hi> Some perſons it ſeems, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtom of the Town-converſe, do divert themſelves in Clubs at Coffee-Houſes, Taverns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where with a certain frankneſs of Converſation, agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a people that abhor ſtarcht pedantry, they toſs the Gazets, and Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences up and down; and ſome one perhaps has pickt up a Pamphlet of more Wit, than Diſcretion, and fuller of Drollery, than Honeſty, which exerciſes and whets what Ingenuity the company can ſpare; now in the Career of diſcourſe, ſome one perhaps applauds what is diſcommendable, another Cenſures that of which he is no Competent Judge; and now for theſe <hi>Sculking</hi> Limitors to Wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw Treaſon out of every wry expreſſion, or miſplaced word, is wretched dunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if it has not a more ſevere and agreeable Name: But theſe Sharkes hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Jaundiſe in their own eyes, think all the world yellow, and whatever of baſeneſs they bear in their own boſoms, preſently conclude it to be working in other mens brains.</p>
            <p>To Conclude (Gentlemen) let their defeated folly teach us Innocent and Loyal Wiſdom, for if the deſigns of Papiſts will not teach us to oppoſe our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited ſtrength againſt their combined Fury, ſome or other will take the <hi>Fools<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap</hi> off from <hi>their heads, and put it upon ours.</hi> If you either divide your ſelves, or ſuffer your ſelves by their little wheadling tricks to be divided, you muſt periſh, either <hi>cruelly by their hands,</hi> or <hi>ſhamefully by your own:</hi> What progreſs their Scouts that creep into your Quarters have made that way, and what hopes they have raiſed upon ſuch progreſs, wiſe men <hi>ſee in the Cauſe,</hi> but Fools only <hi>feel in the Effects.</hi> If like <hi>Eteocles,</hi> and <hi>Polynices,</hi> you cannot maintain concord, alive; your enemies will make the experiement, whether your <hi>Flames and Aſhes</hi> will alſo divide in <hi>Smithfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor let us think it enough to have convicted them of Treaſons, except we can approve our own Loyalty: The <hi>ſmoak of ſuſpicion,</hi> as well as the <hi>fire of <pb facs="tcp:53111:6"/>ſin,</hi> muſt be avoided; 'tis not ſufficient, that brave Engliſh tempers are honeſt, unleſs our Enemies be convinced we are eminently ſo.</p>
            <p>We have yet one encouragement left us, that thoſe bloody and deceitful Men ſhall not Out-live their own Plots, nor live out half their own days: For <hi>the ruled Caſes of Providence upon Record,</hi> do abundantly prove, that where Men deal moſt proudly God is above them; and he whoſe care extends to the meaneſt Fly, his Power controuls the great <hi>Leviathan;</hi> when <hi>Aegyptians purſue,</hi> and the Angel takes off their <hi>Chariot-wheels,</hi> and yet they will <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue ſtill,</hi> they will find it ill ſtriving againſt the Stream and Current of Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative Juſtice; when the <hi>builders of Babel</hi> will go on, and <hi>nothing will be reſtrain'd from them, which they have Imagin'd to do;</hi> the next news we hear is, <hi>Let's go down, and confound their Languages;</hi> And if our Romiſh Adverſaries, not owning that hand of diſappointment, which is ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſtretcht out againſt them, ſhall perſiſt to add one Conſpiracy to another, they may expect their own Policies will find them out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much of trouble to have given, was</hi> your Concern, <hi>and</hi> his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>who is,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured and Worthy GENTLEMEN,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servitour, <hi>R. MANSELL.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novem. 3. 1679.</date> Axe-Yard, Weſtminſter.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53111:6"/>An Exact, Full, and particular NARRATIVE OF THE Popiſh Intrigue, to form a PLOT, AND Then to throw it upon the PROTESTANTS.</head>
         <div type="part">
            <p>IF <hi>Truth</hi> in its <hi>richeſt dreſs,</hi> that is <hi>Nakedneſs,</hi> will pleaſe, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſpair of the Readers acceptation; but if nothing but <hi>Oratory</hi> will recommend <hi>this Piece,</hi> Let him ſeek elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: The nature of a Narrative will not bear it, the Judicious loath it, I have not the faculty to do it, and if I had, am quite out of humour to ſcratch him where it itches, or to gratify a vanity that argues ſo much diſtemper of Soul.</p>
            <p>Whatever is maintained by Wit, by a greater Wit may be deſtroyed; what Rhetorick can ſay for the Plaintiff, it can ſay alſo for the Defendant; only Truth ſincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the eye, takes and captivates all the World: I ſhall not, for ought I know, (as I have not hitherto) call
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53111:7"/>this Contrivance <hi>a horrid, helliſh Deviliſh Conſpiracy,</hi> for when I have Plainly from the beſt Records I could procure, (and I deal openly, I think I have the beſt that are,) laid open <hi>the matter of Fact,</hi> with the profeſſed declared deſignments of it, every Reader will load it with <hi>ſuch Epithets,</hi> and give it more poignant Terms than I can readily invent, who am na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally barren in my Invention.</p>
            <p>I am not curious in my method, but have indulged my own humour in this ſingle point, to repreſent the whole in diſtinct paragraphs, that ſo the meaneſt reader (who deſerves, and may challenge an intereſt in theſe papers,) may more eaſily digeſt that <hi>in parcells,</hi> which perhaps would overſet his capacity if ſwallow'd <hi>in the lump,</hi> and further Preface let not the Reader expect from me.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The whole of the Intrigue was thus much: That whereas the Catholicks former deſign <hi>upon His Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Government; and the deſign of that deſign</hi> to extirpate the Proteſtants, and the Proteſtant Religion, was clearly diſcovered, and probably would now be prevented, and that all their hopeful and promiſing attempts to corrupt the Kings Evidence had to their great ſurprize miſcarried, yet ſtill though ſucceſs were wanting to their endeavours, they would not be wanting to themſelves, but puſh for it once more, that if poſſible they might retreive the game, which ſeem'd utterly loſt to all, but themſelves, who had great faith againſt great diſcouragements. That a Plot might be contrived with ſuch fair probabilities, and preſumptions, having witneſſes laid in at every ſtage to prove the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, which being prudently faſten'd upon the Proteſtants might ſo win upon the belief of His Majeſty, and ſo approve it ſelf to the Conſciences of the Judges, and Juries before whom any of the Plotters ſhould be indicted, arraign'd, and tryed, that the Proteſtants would be found guilty of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the Perſon, and Government of His Majeſty, and thereupon being juſtly and openly ſacrificed to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Law, the Catholicks might appear, as they have confidently avowed themſelves, to be <hi>the Kings beſt Subjects;</hi> and then it might be left to the Ingenuity of the Impartial
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53111:7"/>world to draw this concluſion, <hi>That it was now evident that the laſt years Plot, which by the malicious Artifices of the Hereticks, had been father'd upon the Innocent Catholicks, was but a colour to take away their Lives, and ſieze their Eſtates, which being conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, was ſufficient to render them guilty with thoſe whoſe covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had prepared them for the ſpoil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the ſubſtance of what in the ſequel of this Narrative ſhall brancht out into its particulars, in which the <hi>Narrator does moſt ſolemnly, and religiouſly promiſe to ſurrender him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ſlave to Truth, Faithfulneſs, and Impartiality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be obſerved, that though the Papiſts were ſo active in forming this <hi>New Treaſon</hi> for the Proteſtants, yet they had not laid aſide their own; but with the ſame Zeal preſſ'd for the aſſaſſinating of His Sacred Majeſty as before; whether their rage were the <hi>more inflamed becauſe it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd;</hi> or that like loſing Gameſters they were reſolved <hi>to double the ſtake or quit all;</hi> or whether thy fancied they had got <hi>better inſtruments to effect that out-work,</hi> with which all their other deſignes muſt ſucceed proportionably. I ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for theſe any, or all of theſe or other Reaſons it was, 'tis none of my part to determine, only <hi>that thus it was,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> in his information upon Oath before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> aſſures us, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation was taken, <hi>Octob.</hi> 31. 1679. <hi>I was ſent for to the</hi> Tower, <hi>whither I went in diſguiſe, and after much diſcourſe with my Lord</hi> [Powis] <hi>in the dining Room, he took me into his Chamber, and there was the</hi> Lord Arundel, <hi>who firſt ſaid</hi> (after ſome diſcourſe) <hi>will you do any thing to make your Fortune? I anſwered yes! I would do any thing! well then ſaid he</hi> will you kill the King for a good Reward? <hi>I was amaz'd, and ſaid, Sir, you jeſt ſurely? then he again asked me: and I ſaid,</hi> any Body but the King and His Royal Brother, <hi>Nay ſaid he, I mean not ſo. But Tell me, will ye do it? I again anſwered, no! without time to conſider o'nt; Then ſaid my</hi> Lord Powis, <hi>No! no! come!</hi> Lord Arundel <hi>does only this to try you; and pray my</hi> Lord Arundel (ſays Lord Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis) <hi>what will you give him to do ſo? 'tis worth</hi> (ſaid Lord A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundel) 2000
<abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>No! no!</hi> (<hi>ſaid</hi> Lord Powis) <hi>you ſhall do that to my Lord</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>and ſhall have</hi> 500
<abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>for your Reward:</hi> 
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53111:8"/>[but of the Honourable Perſons intereſt in their hatred, in its proper place:] the ſame Deponent ſays further, <hi>That when he had acquainted the Lord</hi> Peterburgh, that Sir Robert Peyton <hi>would meet him at</hi> Mr. Gadburies <hi>houſe, the next Tueſday night at</hi> 5 <hi>a Clock; he went alſo to</hi> Mr. Gadburies, <hi>and gave him notice of it: who liked it well, but was angry that I had diſpleaſed the Lords in the</hi> Tower, <hi>and eſpecially the Lord</hi> Caſtlemain, <hi>who did deſign to make my fortune: I demanded if he knew the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occaſion of their Anger, he anſwered, yes; it was becauſe I would not kill the King. I wonder at you</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when you knew no way to get out of Priſon whilſt you lived (had not good Charity done it) that you ſhould refuſe it: nay it might ſo eaſily have been done, by your own hand, that no hurt could have befallen you. Why, ſaid I,</hi> Mr. Gadbury, <hi>can it be any other but death? yes, with you</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>for before you were releaſed out of Priſon, I had by</hi> Mrs. Celliers <hi>a true Account what time you were born, and the Counteſs of</hi> Powis <hi>ordered me to Calculate your Nativity, and it is ſo clear, that you were adjudged by all a perſon allotted to that bold and daring Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize;</hi> and in Mr. <hi>Willoughbie's</hi> further examination before the Council-board, <hi>Nov.</hi> 1. 1679. he affirms <hi>That after he had been introduced to the King by</hi> Mr. Chiffinch, <hi>where he had been alone with His Majeſty in his Cloſet, and told</hi> Mrs. Cellier <hi>that he had ſo been;</hi> O, ſaid ſhe, <hi>what an opportunity have you loſt?</hi> and ſoon after the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> ſaid the ſame thing, in Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier's</hi> hearing, And, <hi>how bravely he might have killed the King if he had been provided!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This Plot was unanimouſly agreed, ſhould in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and diſcurſive part of it only touch <hi>the Presbyterians;</hi> if I ſhould adventure the credit of this one point upon <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame,</hi> it were no vain thing, for the Ears of all men were alarmed with a continual noiſe of a <hi>Presbyterian Plot;</hi> the Pamphlets rung of nothing but a <hi>Presbyterian Plot;</hi> and the Coffee-houſes ecchoed to the common Prints, a <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Plot;</hi> ſo that the Eyes of all who received the Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were fixt upon that kind of men, as the quarter from whence this prognoſticated ſtorm would ariſe: but I ſhall not content my ſelf, much leſs the Reader, to reſt this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation upon popular outcry, but ſhew that it was <hi>a deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53111:8"/>and a politickly deſigned thing too:</hi> Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, of <hi>October</hi> 31. 1679. Depoſes to this purpoſe, <hi>That the Counteſs</hi> [Powis] <hi>told him he muſt go into</hi> Buckingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire <hi>to one</hi> Mrs. Webb's <hi>at</hi> Peterley, <hi>with a Letter to one</hi> Mrs. Jean; <hi>and when he came thither, he finds this</hi> Mrs. Jean, <hi>not a Woman, but a Man, nay a Prieſt; who immediately upon reading the Letter, made him Confeſs and Receive the Sacrament, to be true to the whole cauſe: and this</hi> Jeane, <hi>made up the Papers for the Plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> Presbyrians: <hi>which</hi> [Paper] <hi>was only the ground of it, and was to be drawn up by the Lords, and</hi> Mr. Nevil, (<hi>as he told</hi> Mr. Dangerfield. And afterwards Mr. <hi>Woods, told me the Lords had conſulted together, that before</hi> Oates <hi>was Indicted, there ſhould a Rumour be ſpread abroad of a Plot amongſt the</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, <hi>and ſomething of it made appear;</hi> and that I may not be tedious in a matter ſo acknowledged, he further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, <hi>That one</hi> Dowdel <hi>came to him with</hi> 27 <hi>Letters to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, moſt of them written by</hi> Mr. Nevils <hi>own hand, That</hi> Mr. Turner <hi>the Lord</hi> Powis <hi>his Prieſt deſired</hi> Mrs. Cellier <hi>to get ſome Catholicks to write out ſeveral Copies which he then had; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhe ſent for one</hi> Singe <hi>a School-maſter, who wrote there a week more or leſs. The Contents of as many of them (as I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (ſays he) are as follows;</hi>
               <q rend="inline">'That their buſineſs here at <hi>London</hi> went on very well, and hoped theirs did the ſame in the Country, and Commiſſions would ſhortly be ready; mentioning in ſome Letters, many Noble Perſons Names: and that we will now be our own chooſers in matters of Government, and take our own pleaſures, with Popery:'</q> 
               <hi>Many or moſt of them Importing the ſame ſenſe with thoſe taken by the Cuſtom-Houſe Officers,</hi> &amp;c.<hi>Theſe were to be ſent into all parts of the Kingdom where any</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians <hi>Lived, to be put into their Houſes privately, and then by ſome other Perſons, the Houſe to be ſearcht, and theſe Papers produced in Teſtimony againſt them:</hi> This is the fact, ſo it was, and ſo they projected the matter, and judg'd themſelves very politick in the projection: for how readily would the ſparks of ſuch a ſuggeſtion take with great Multitudes <hi>againſt the Presbyterians,</hi> when their old animoſity did yet <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53111:9"/>ſmoother, nor could the old grudge be quenched: And though many rayled at the Presbyterians out of cuſtom, becauſe they had contracted <hi>an evil habit of rayling</hi> and could not leave it; others <hi>from Example,</hi> ſwearing and rayling becauſe their Companions whetted their already too keen inclinations; others perhaps <hi>out of Ignorance,</hi> who neither knew what a <hi>Presbyterian, nor Presbytery was,</hi> yet it was a Common Theme to rail on, and therefore were the more ready at it; yet the Deſigners had a further reach, to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Proteſtant Cauſe, by rendring ſo many of them unſerviceable to the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> which by ſuch ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous reflexions they muſt needs be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another ſtep I would make is this: However the vogue carried it for <hi>a Presbyterian Plot,</hi> yet the inſide was <hi>a Proteſtant plot,</hi> which if my proper Province were to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon out the matter might be eaſily demonſtrated; for the Church of <hi>England</hi> is an object more adaequate to Papal <hi>Covetouſneſs, and Envy,</hi> then the Diſſenters and their Friends can ſhow; what great temptation is there in the Skins of a few half-ſtarved Non-Conformiſts, when the Revenues of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and fair Eſtates of the Nobility and Gentry of that Communion, were a morſel that might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken the dulleſt appetite; but <hi>the fact</hi> is that I muſt clear: let it therefore be noted, of All thoſe Noble Perſons that they had nominated for <hi>a Council of State</hi> to manage this War againſt the Government, <hi>not above one</hi> could be with any tolerable propriety of ſpeech called <hi>Presbyterian:</hi> none being more worthy Perſonages, nor any more really, and zealouſly devoted to the true Intereſt of this Church: The <hi>Duke of Monmouth</hi> whom they created General over this ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Army; the Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerrard, and his Son,</hi> who with Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong</hi> were Commiſſioned for <hi>Leiutenant Generals,</hi> were none of them ever ſuſpected of Presbyterianiſme, and ſhould I look over the Clubbs, where the <hi>Meal Tubb Intelligence</hi> informs us, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were there employed <hi>as Writers and Meſſengers into <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53111:9"/>the Country, when occaſion ſhould require were all to be Field Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> yet amongſt theſe I cannot pick out half a dozen Presbyterians, and its harſh to denominate an Army that muſt overturn the Government of three Kingdoms, from ſo inconſiderable a Number: but of this there will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evidence, when we come to exemplifie the platform of this deſign as it was laid in the above-mentioned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Having got this general Idaea of the Plot in their Heads, which yet was not a peice of exact proportion, but left to more mature Counſels to be poliſhed. It was time to think, and pitch upon <hi>fit Inſtruments</hi> for the executing of it, that is to make it ſtick to thoſe perſons, <hi>whoſe forward Zeal againſt the late Popiſh deſign againſt His Majeſties Perſon, Government, and the Proteſtant Religion, had made muſt obnoxious to their Malice, and revenge:</hi> And herein they proceeded with much caution, as became their wiſdoms, who knew well, that many well laid deſignes, ſuch as promiſed great hopes of a good iſſue had miſcarried through the inſufficiency of thoſe to whoſe Hands the management was committed: <hi>Madam Cellier,</hi> by Calling a Midwife, whoſe Employ chiefly was with Catholick Ladies, and Gentlewomen, was very ſerviceable in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Catholick Cauſe of this birth, wherewith it had gone ſo long, and was now in the pangs, and throws of bringing forth. This Gentlewoman by the means of one Mrs. <hi>White,</hi> was brought to Mr. <hi>Danger field,</hi> than a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate:</hi> She there examined his capableneſs for buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and becauſe Inſtruments may be uſed but cannot be formed, for a trial of his Abilities. <hi>Let me ſee</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>how you can draw up Articles againſt</hi> Captain Richardſon. Hereupon ſhe gave him Inſtructions, who performed the firſt Eſſay of his Art to her ſatisfaction, and then told him, <hi>She had ſomething of greater moment for him to undertake:</hi> but Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> being then a Priſoner, ſome Expedient muſt be uſed for his Enlargement, that he might enter upon his charge; and to this end ſhe adviſes him to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53111:10"/>to Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> in whom ſhe would make ſuch an Intereſt by <hi>Alderman Jefferies,</hi> as to get his Petition grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Then ſhe employs one Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> a Sollicitor to Bail him out, which yet could not be effected in leſs then three weeks: however <hi>Madam Cellier</hi> ſent her Maid <hi>Margret</hi> every day to ſupply his wants with mony, to ſupport his Spirits with good words ſuch as adminiſtred hope, and not long after he was bailed: after that this charitable Perſon through whoſe hands much of the <hi>Romiſh benevolence paſſed,</hi> had cleared the Fees, and expenſes of the Priſon.</p>
            <p>But he was no ſooner diſcharg'd from <hi>Newgate,</hi> but <hi>he vvas Arreſted, and thrown into the Counter;</hi> This ſurpriz'd Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> yet ſhe ſends her truſty Maid <hi>Margaret</hi> to aſſure him, <hi>that if he vvould forthvvith be at Liberty, ſhe vvould purchaſe it at any rate, for ſhe had ordered buſineſs for him the Tueſday next;</hi> And firſt <hi>ſhe furniſhes him vvith mony to remove himſelf to the Kings-Bench</hi> by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> here he is releived by her again, <hi>receiving twenty ſhillings in hand, and twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings per week, with promiſes of a ſpeedy Releaſe:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the good of the Catholick Cauſe was the main end that muſt overrule leſſer projects, ſhe had found a notable job of work for him there, which was to practiſe upon one Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> then and there a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, whoſe ſtory will he taken up in due order: here a peice of ſervice was alſo enjoyned him with Captain <hi>Bedlow,</hi> by the Lords in the Tower, (as Mr. <hi>Mounſon</hi> told him) viz. <hi>that he ſhould ſend for the Captain, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending he knew ſomething of the Plot, when he was in</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>that he would gladly diſcover it, if he might be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd, which would be a great piece of Service to the Lords; firſt being ſworn an evidence for the King, and then to ſwear ſuch other matters as</hi> Mr. Mounſon <hi>ſhould inſtruct him in, but becauſe they could not Contrive any ſecure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to proceed upon in his treating with</hi> Captain Bedlow <hi>the buſineſs fell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53111:10"/>Some while after being furniſht with Money (as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes) by the Lords <hi>Powis, Petre, Arundel, Bellaſis,</hi> and <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> to Compound his Debts, and Five pound given him by M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Cellier</hi> to clear his Fees, Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> is fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</p>
            <p>And being at Liberty after ſo long durance in ſeveral Priſons, he lookt on himſelf a competent Undertaker in the greateſt Affairs, and was brought by M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Cellier</hi> to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> who <hi>thank'd him for his diligence in the buſineſs of the</hi> Kings-bench, <hi>and withall told him, that his faithfulneſs in that Affair ſhould make his Fortune, provided he would undertake other buſineſs;</hi> which he promis'd to doe.</p>
            <p>But now he muſt come under Diſcipline, to make him tight to the Cauſe; and accordingly is charged <hi>to continue ſteadfaſt in his Religion,</hi> (what that was, perhaps every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, perhaps no body knows) <hi>to Confeſs once a Week to Mr.</hi> Mounſon, <hi>which he promiſed to doe.</hi> And <hi>indeed, when he was in the</hi> Kings-bench, <hi>he was adviſed to</hi> ſcowre his Kettle, <hi>that is, to Confeſs, and Receive;</hi> but becauſe his Practices would need a little latitude, <hi>he was Indulged to be drunk with</hi> Strode, <hi>and told it was no ſin, becauſe it was for the good of the Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being thus prepared, it was time he ſhould be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; and ſo he was, the Counteſs <hi>Powis</hi> ſends <hi>him with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Lord</hi> Caſtlemain, <hi>who received him kindly, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make his Fortune, if he would uſe his endeavour to ſupport the Catholick Cauſe:</hi> and preſently returns him with a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Letter to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> to this purpoſe: <hi>This perſon I like well, and though he be no Scholar, yet he may ſerve to inſtruct the Youths, according as he ſhall be directed, and in ſo doing, I ſhall be eaſed of much ſuspicion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> muſt go into <hi>Buckingham-ſhire,</hi> to Madam, or Mounſieur <hi>Jeane,</hi> (for it was a Prieſt in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans diſguiſe) and from him he receives <hi>the Rudiments of this Presbyterian Plott;</hi> and comes up to the Lords in the Tower, to have it reduc'd to a conſiſtent Form: And when Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was ſent with a Letter to the Lady <hi>Tuke,</hi> ſhe ſeem'd <hi>to like him well, and ſent word he was fit to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53111:11"/>and gave him <hi>two Guinneys;</hi> and askt him, <hi>If he was one that durſt do any thing of deſperate conſequence:</hi> He anſwers, <hi>Yes!</hi> But the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> meeting with ſome Rub in an Affair ſhe had with a Noble Perſon, and not being able to procure Mr. <hi>Mounſon</hi> out of Priſon to be an Aſſiſtant in this grand Intrigue, tells Mr. <hi>Dangerfield, I thought I could have got Mr.</hi> Mounſon <hi>out, but ſince it can no better be, you muſt do all our buſineſs; and from that night by order of the Lords ſent by Mris.</hi> Cellier, <hi>he was to fall upon the execution of this black Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> is now Plenipotentiary to manage the whole Negotiation, under the Conduct of his great Lords and Maſters; and that he might the better expect ſucceſs, they conſult how to prepare the People to receive and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Story ſo incredible, that the Proteſtants would actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Rebell: Their firſt attempt was, by diſperſing ſeveral ſcandalous Pamphlets, written by <hi>Nevill,</hi> and others, againſt the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to refreſh the Peoples Memories with any old Actions of theirs, which might render it credible: And the next was, that by ſeveral Agents aſſign'd to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Poſts, the Coffee-houſes might ring of the general apprehenſions of ſome Notorious Villanies ready to break forth from the Presbyterian party. This Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, <hi>That he gave the Papers he received from Mr.</hi> Jean <hi>in</hi> Bucks, <hi>to the Lady</hi> Powis, <hi>who open'd, and read them, to this effect: That good ſtore of Pamphlets muſt be writ and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad againſt the Presbyterians, and perſons muſt be employed to goe to Coffee-houſes, and rail againſt the Presbyterians, and if they met with any that offer'd to contend, matters of Treaſon or ſome ſuch thing might eaſily be laid to their Charge, and ſo have them ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but there muſt be many perſons employed in theſe matters, and it would be great prudence not to let them know one another, nor any one to know more than the part he was to act:</hi> And again; <hi>From that night, by the Lords Order ſent me, I began going about to Coffee-houſes, and had an Account from</hi> Nevill <hi>what to goe to; and I choſe</hi> Farrs <hi>Coffee-houſe; whither I went every night, till Mr.</hi> Kinnaſton <hi>and I differ'd.</hi> And here it ſeems for want <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53111:11"/>of other idleneſs, his diſcourſe was (as the Lords had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him) <hi>That Sir</hi> Edm. Bury Godfrey <hi>was Murther'd by my Lord</hi> Danby<hi>'s Order, who joyn'd with the Presbyterians to overthrow the Catholicks:</hi> A ſtory ſo incredible, as might juſtly ſhake the credit of the reſt amongſt conſidering perſons: Then <hi>he was ſent to drop the</hi> Danby Reflections, <hi>and</hi> Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Touchſtone, <hi>and divers other baſe Pamphlets written by</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, <hi>in the Coffee-houſes, and to ſend them ſealed up in Papers to</hi> Man's <hi>Coffee-houſe, to</hi> Farrs, <hi>and to</hi> Proctors, <hi>and others:</hi> Let us note by the way, that this Mr. <hi>Nevill</hi> was a perſon great in repute for the happineſs of his Pen; And I have been credibly informed from the Minutes of the Council, that Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> before the Honourable Board affirm'd, <hi>Nov.</hi> 7. 79. <hi>Fryd. afternoon;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Mr.</hi> Nevill <hi>by the advice of the Lords in the Tower, ſhould be again confined; foraſmuch as when he was formerly in that Condition, he had been very induſtrious in writing of Papers in their buſineſs, but now he was at liberty, he chiefly follow'd the Play-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Information of Mr. <hi>Bedford,</hi> Nov. 4. before the Council, is very remarkable; <hi>That about ſix weeks before, he went with Mr.</hi> Willoughby <hi>to one</hi> Thompſon <hi>in</hi> Fetter-lane, <hi>who was then printing</hi> The <hi>Presbyterian Unmasked;</hi> in which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous piece, if the Reader will conſult it, there are intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>of great havock that would ſuddenly be made by</hi> John Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, <hi>but that vengeance would ſuddenly overtake them;</hi> And this may further be obſerved, that this <hi>Thompſon</hi> has been a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Engine in all Popiſh Deſigns, and to this day abuſes the World with his <hi>weekly Domeſtick Intelligence.</hi> And laſtly, let me note but one Paragraph more out of his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>I met</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>ſoon after at Mris.</hi> Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, <hi>and told her of their proceedings, who liked it well, but told me, I muſt go forward, with all ſpeed, in ſome Intrigue againſt the Duke came to Town, to make him believe the Presbyterians were plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the King; then the Way was conſulted, and the next day upon Mris.</hi> Celliers <hi>return from the Lady</hi> Powis, <hi>who had ſent for her to the Tower, ſhe told me, I muſt give Money to ſome people that were idle, and appear'd well, to go to the Coffee-houſes and <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53111:12"/>Clubs, and endeavour to learn how things ſtood;</hi> where <hi>I ſound all things very hot againſt the</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>and that the Plot was diſcover'd to be theirs; This being firſt ſet on foot by ſome of our Accomplices, as</hi> Wood, Dormer, <hi>the</hi> Virginia <hi>Merchant,</hi> Gadbury, <hi>and divers others, and I was to further it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe this was a matter of great moment, and that upon the right conduct thereof, the Proſperity of their whole Cauſe depended; It was thought adviſeable to crave Foreign Counſels, and accordingly a Letter was ſent to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Holder,</hi> ſtating the whole Deſign, and earneſtly deſiring his Advice therein; and further, to <hi>procure the Impreſſions of ſeveral Coats of Arms to be cut there, which were fixt to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of the Letter;</hi> which Letter was conveyed by one M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Katherine Holder,</hi> living in St. <hi>James</hi>'s, to her Uncle; and in one of the Anſwers to theſe Letters, <hi>I heard</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi>) <hi>the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>read as follows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you had taken this Courſe ſooner, much blood might have been ſaved; but I doubt 'tis now too late, and fear the St.</hi> Omers Teſtimony <hi>being ſo baffled, has much empair'd our endeavours, yet to my power I will aſſiſt, and adviſe you to goe on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Though matters ſeem'd ſo well concerted, yet there were ſome difficulties in the way, which in order to a happy procedure muſt be removed; And the greateſt Obſtacle in their way, was <hi>the Life of the Earl of Shaftsbury:</hi> A perſon whoſe fixedneſs to the true Intereſt of his Majeſty, and the Proteſtant Religion, they well knew; whoſe profound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to dive into all Myſteries, and whoſe Wiſdom to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate their Deſigns they feared; and therefore his Perſon was by them mortally hated, and nothing can quench their fiery rage but his Blood.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Abergaveney</hi> told Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> it was <hi>as eaſie for him to kill the Lord</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>as a Bird on a Tree;</hi> and when he demanded, <hi>How?</hi> ſhe then and there propoſed Divers ways, ſaying, <hi>She was often with the ſaid Lord, who talked ſo cruelly againſt the Catholicks, that ſhe could not endure to hear it, but yet was forced to hold a Candle to the Devil;</hi> amongſt others (wherein Mr. <hi>Knolles</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sharp</hi> alſo agreed) one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53111:12"/>was, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Dangerfield <hi>ſhould pretend himſelf a perſon good at Curing the Gout; and that ſhe would recommend him to the ſaid Lord; this the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>liked well, but ſaid, ſhe would let the Lords know it:</hi> And now if by this Expedient he could be admitted to ſuch a nearneſs to his Lordſhips perſon, he might have pickt ſome convenient time to Cure him of that, and all other Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>We muſt remember, that when Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was in the Tower with the Lords <hi>Powis</hi> and <hi>Arundel,</hi> who offer'd 2000
<abbr>l.</abbr> for the Murder of the King; that being refuſed, <hi>Immediately</hi> 500 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>was offered for the Murdering the Earl of Shaftsbury;</hi> and when Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> asked them how it might be atchieved? they both replyed, <hi>Eaſily enough: For</hi> (ſaid the Lord <hi>Powis</hi>) <hi>two nights ſince my man</hi> Woods <hi>was there to deliver a Meſſage, and he ſorely repented he was not provided, though there more twenty or more perſons in the Room: But if he were out of the way</hi> (ſaid the Lord <hi>Powis</hi>) <hi>we might eaſily overrun the reſt of our Oppoſites: Then</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) <hi>I promiſed I would, and the Lord</hi> Powis <hi>gave me ten Guinneys, and told me, a</hi> Virginia <hi>Merchant ſhould come to me the Sunday following, to Mris.</hi> Celliers <hi>houſe, and adviſe with me about it: And accordingly this Merchant came at the time, and place appointed, who entred into diſcourſe with me about it, and I ſeem'd to be very willing to undertake it; and he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed me to conſult with Mr.</hi> Dormer, <hi>and all the perſons concern'd therein, how to carry it on, and on Munday I went to</hi> Confeſſion <hi>to Mr.</hi> Knowles, <hi>and received the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet ſtill ſomething or other Intervened, which deferred the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deſign againſt the Lord</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>till the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>came to me, and bid me</hi> (theſe are his own words) <hi>go to Mr.</hi> Sharp <hi>to Confeſſion, and Receive, for I muſt ſpeedily, or on the next Order, go to the Lord</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>I did then go and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and Receive of Mr.</hi> Sharp, <hi>who conjur'd me by all that was good, to uſe all ſpeed imaginable for the ſtabbing the Lord</hi> Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, <hi>which I promiſed to doe, and left him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Mris.</hi> Cellier <hi>received a Letter that night;</hi> that I muſt go to the ſaid Lord, and ſay as follows: <hi>My Lord, I am a Stranger, and am neither introduced, nor ſent by any Perſon, but deſire to know if it be in my power to ſerve your Lordſhip, if your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53111:13"/>Honour will ſhew me favour? Then Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>gave me</hi> a Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, (<hi>three or four ſuch being brought to her the Sunday before by the</hi> Virginia <hi>Merchant</hi>) <hi>and diſpatcht me away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Dangerfield</hi> (under the Name of Mr. <hi>Day</hi>) addreſſes himſelf to this famous Exployt; and coming to the Earls houſe, deſires a Servant to acquaint his Lord, that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had ſome Affairs with him of great Importance: His Lordſhip commands him to be conducted into the Dining<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room, whither his Lordſhip, as ſoon as he had diſpatch thoſe perſons who attended him, came, waited on by his Servants. <hi>Mr.</hi> Day <hi>intimates to him, that he had ſomething to diſcover to his</hi> Honour, <hi>of the higheſt Concern for his Lordſhip to know, but withall ſuch as required the greateſt ſecreſie, and therefore humbly requeſted, that his Servants might be diſcharged their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent attendance;</hi> which his Lordſhip as peremptorily refuſing as it was importunately urged, Mr. <hi>Day</hi> replyed, That <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had not his Proofs ready at preſent, which yet in a little time he ſhould, he would take his leave at preſent, and within a few dayes wait again on his Lordſhip;</hi> and for that time he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> at his return gives an account to Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> That <hi>he was diſappointed, but would take ſome other opportunity;</hi> ſhe gives advice of this to the Tower: And about two dayes after, meeting with the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> at Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> ſhe tells him, he muſt go again to the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s, and tell him as follows, <hi>Viz. That if he ſhould be ſent for before the King and Council, and there have ſeveral Impeachments of High Treaſon drawn againſt him, and be thence committed to the Tower, and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in many of the ſaid Impeachments to be from Letters written with his own hand, that then I might hope his Lordſhip would believe I was his faithfull Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus inſtructed, Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> attends <hi>the Earl</hi> (being arm'd as before with his Dagger) his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> being in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with <hi>a perſon of Honour,</hi> commanded Mr. <hi>Day</hi> to be put into a Chamber which had a paſſage into <hi>the Dining Room,</hi> till his Lordſhip could be at leiſure. Mr. <hi>Day</hi> thought he might now effect his matters, and coming ſoftly into the Entry that leads to the Dining-Room, ſtood liſtning to hear when that Noble Perſonage ſhould depart, preſuming, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53111:13"/>it fell out, that the Lords Servants would wait on that Noble Lord down to his Coach, and that the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> being for a while left alone, he might diſpatch him, and clear himſelf of the Houſe before the return of the Servants. As ſoon as that Nobleman departed, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants there waited on him down the Stairs, but unhappily for Mr. <hi>Day;</hi> juſt at that Lords going out, came another Gentleman in, who entertain'd his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> with ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; but Mr. <hi>Day</hi> hearing no voice, preſum'd the happy hour was come, and therefore throwing open the door, was coming up towards his Lordſhip, when he unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſpies a young Gentleman with him: This ſurprized him, and finding the ſeaſon loſt, he retires to the Room where he was before. This Action gave ſome apprehenſion to his Lordſhip, who as ſoon as his Servants were returned, and the Gentleman withdrawn, ſends for Mr. <hi>Day</hi> to come to him; who after his former Preface, That he had matters of great Concern to communicate to his Lordſhip, deſired that his Servants might be commanded to withdraw; but his Lordſhip being ſomewhat the more awaken'd by the late Carriage of Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> told him, He muſt not expect that from him, but that if he had buſineſs of moment to Impart, as he pretended, he ſhould impart it: He thereupon begins to tell his Lordſhip; that he was in danger of being queſtioned for his Life; that his Servants were falſe to him, that they did copy out his Letters and Papers, and communicated them, whence would be drawn matter to form an Impeachment againſt him: His Lordſhip askt, Which of his Servants they were that had thus Copied out his Writings? And when Mr. <hi>Day</hi> replyed, That he knew not; his Honour return'd, <hi>Sir, I can now tell you, that every word of what you ſay is falſe; for I have no Papers, no Letters, which if known to all the World would endanger one hair of my head; and therefore it cannot be that any ſuch Impeachment ſhould be form'd out of any Letters of mine:</hi> If that be your Lordſhips opinion, (anſwer'd Mr. <hi>Day</hi>) I ſhall take my leave.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Day</hi> being thus a ſecond time diſappointed, <hi>ſends the Lords word of it by his Boy;</hi> and the next day Mr. <hi>Woods</hi> came, and ſaid, <hi>His Lord wonder'd I had been ſo great a Coward;</hi> and <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53111:14"/>ſo order'd Mr. <hi>Day</hi> alias <hi>Dangerfield</hi> to goe to the King, and tell him that he had been again with the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> leſt the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſhould firſt acquaint his Majeſty with it.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ſends him to Lord, <hi>Peterburghs,</hi> to tell him what had happen'd, and how he had been twice at Lord <hi>Shaftsburies;</hi> and he was well pleaſed (as Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> upon Oath informs,) and promiſed him, <hi>when any Forces were raiſed, he would put in for a Regiment of Horſe, then he would make Mr.</hi> Dangerfield <hi>Captain of a Troop:</hi> And added, <hi>Be ſure you do his buſineſs the third time.</hi> And when the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> came next to Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> ſhe would have perſwaded him <hi>to a third attempt upon the Lord</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>which he refuſing, ſhe ſtruck him gently with her Fan on the hand, calling him</hi> Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Fellow, <hi>and ſaid, She her ſelf would goe.</hi> But Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> anſwered, <hi>No Madam, that ſhall never be, for I will make the World know, That our Sex are braver than they of the Maſculine, and my ſelf will goe and do the work.</hi> To which the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> returned, <hi>Alas! all our men of Courage are ſent out of the world, or ſecured for to be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhe was as good as her word as to the Attempting part; for the ſame, or the very next day, this Virago, that deſerves a place amongſt the worthy Confeſſors in the <hi>Roman Calendar,</hi> viſited his Lordſhip, and Complementing his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip highly for his Moderation towards the Catholicks, would have inſinuated her ſelf into his good thoughts; but his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip made perhaps more cautelous by the late demeanour of Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> kept a ſtrict eye upon her, <hi>and obſerving her to be fumbling about her Petticoat, or Pockets,</hi> gently (as if between Jeſt and Earneſt) layd his hands upon hers, and pleaſantly drolled with her, till ſhe ſeemed ready to take her leave; but ſhe was not gone far towards the door, but that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon her ſelf, that ſhe ſhould promiſe ſo high, and come off doing as little as Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> whoſe Cowardiſe ſhe had ſcorned, ſhe ſuddenly returns towards his Lordſhip; which he obſerving, ſteps to her, and laying his hands on hers as before, daſht her out of Countenance, that ſhe was forced to depart, to tell a ſad ſtory of her failure to thoſe who waited to ſee the fruit of her great and daring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53111:14"/>8. Theſe Conſpirators being thus fruſtrated in their deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Death of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> yet were not diſcouraged in the main of their Contrivance, which was to faſten this grand Treaſon againſt His Majeſties Perſon and Government, upon the Proteſtants: And therefore being reſolved to drive the Nail home, it was judged abſolutely neceſſary to poſſeſs His Majeſty with it: A mighty Point it would be, if they could make it, to impoſe ſo far upon His Majeſties well-known Judgment. That His Proteſtant Subjects ſhould grow ſo weary of His Perſon, and Government, as to deſire a change, when he knew that they knew how much their Intereſt, and that of their Religion was wrapt up in His Majeſties Life and Proſperity: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would firſt endeavour to lodge this Intreague with His Royal Highneſs, who being then returned to Town, the Lord <hi>Peterborough</hi> (ſays <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) <hi>ſent for me to give him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this New Plot, but I was unprovided: But I met with Mr.</hi> Woods, <hi>and he ſate down, and wrote what came uppermoſt, or what he was ordered</hi> (at leaſt as he told me) <hi>but ſome things I was forc'd to put in alſo. Then the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>recommended me to the Lord</hi> Peterborough, <hi>and deſired him by a Letter which Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>carried</hi> (as ſhe told me) <hi>to take me to His</hi> R. Highneſs, <hi>which he did; but firſt demanded of me what I could ſay? or if the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>had given me any Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the ſame: We ſtaid in the Lord</hi> Peterboroughs <hi>Cloſet in his Lodgings in</hi> Whitehall, <hi>for ſome time, till the D. returned from Supper, then he took me and Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>to the</hi> D<hi rend="sup">s.</hi> 
               <hi>Cloſet, where we both had the honour to kiſs his Royal Hand; and me he took from the ground where I was kneeling, and then I delivered the Papers, and ſpoke according to my Orders. After this the Lord</hi> Peterborough <hi>told me, I muſt go again to the D. as by his Lordſhips means I did, and His R. Highneſs told me I muſt go to the King, and give His Majeſty an account at large of all that the Papers mentioned, and told me the King would order me money to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the Diſcovery, and then he gave me twenty Guinneys; and I came away, and gave an account to the Lords of all; and that I muſt go to the King, and deſired to know what I must ſay: That night I received no Anſwer more than that the Lady</hi> Powis <hi>would be with me the next day at three of the Clock, and ſo ſhe was, at Mrs.</hi> Celliers <hi>houſe, where ſhe told me, I muſt ſtick hard</hi> [againſt the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> D. of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> Lord D. of <hi>Ducks,</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Waller,</hi> 
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53111:15"/>Coll. <hi>Blood,</hi> and divers others] <hi>And that I muſt tell what Clubs I had enquired out, and where, and that they were all of the Faction; and that if His Majeſty had died at</hi> Windſor, <hi>they had poſted about the Town and Suburbs, a conſiderable Army, to have taken poſſeſsion of the Government, and did deſign to bring the ſame to a Common-wealth, and ſet up the D. of</hi> Monmouth <hi>therein; and that the</hi> Lord Shaftsbury, <hi>and others, were iſſuing out Commiſsions to that effect, and had promiſed ſome to divers perſons; and that I had the promiſe of a Commiſsion from one of the Presbyterian Party:</hi> To this effect I told His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty, no doubt, ſaw through this thin Contrivance, and yet that he might not ſeem wholly to reject an Information that pretended ſo highly to his Service, <hi>he encouraged me</hi> (ſays <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi>) <hi>and ordered</hi> Coll. <hi>Halſall, that I might be furniſht with monies, and I received ſoon after from the ſaid Coll.</hi> 40 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>who told me, I muſt make out things plainer, or the King would not be well pleaſed; which I promiſed to do, and ſo took my leave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> now goes home, and ſends Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> to the Tower, to let the Lords know what had happen'd, and all were well pleaſed, and much rejoyced at his good ſucceſs; but deſired he would not apply himſelf any more to the King, by the means of Coll. <hi>Halſall,</hi> for they believed he would diſcover him.</p>
            <p n="9">9. What Informations were given to His Majeſty at this and other times by Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> we muſt now make out from <hi>that Book found in Mrs.</hi> Celliers <hi>houſe, in a Meal-Tub, by Sir</hi> William Waller, <hi>whoſe diligence nothing could eſcape, whoſe induſtry no pains could weary; and whoſe courage no terrours of Popiſh Enemies could abate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A true and exact Copy of the Book found by Sir</hi> Will. Waller <hi>at Mrs.</hi> Celliers <hi>houſe in the Meal-Tub on Wedneſday,</hi> Octob. 29. 1679.</p>
            <p>Major <hi>Alſop</hi>'s promiſe to me for a Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Goodings</hi> promiſe to ſupport <hi>D. M.</hi> if baniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> night the 12th. of <hi>Septemb. D. Monm.</hi> went to the Sun-Tavern to converſe with <hi>Player</hi> and <hi>Jencks,</hi> for the ſetling Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and alſo a ſupply for himſelf if baniſhed.</p>
            <p>The manner of the meeting of four ſeveral Clubs, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the <hi>King's-Head Tavern,</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon Tavern,</hi> at the <hi>Sun-Tavern,</hi> and one at a <hi>Chandlers-Shop in Weſtminſter,</hi> which are at preſent employed, as Writers and Meſſengers, into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53111:15"/>but when occaſion ſhall require, they are to be Field-Officers.</p>
            <p>The manner of ſending thoſe Meſſengers.</p>
            <p>The manner of their meeting for the better concurrence of all matters.</p>
            <p>Their way of contributing, how often, and for what purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it is done.</p>
            <p>The poſture they were in for a Riſing in the City, if His Majeſty had died.</p>
            <p>The deſign of Riſing in the North to joyn with the Scots, and what ſhall occaſion that Riſing there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gooding</hi>'s Account of the <hi>Chief Perſons and Commanders</hi> there among them, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Hallifax,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Radnor,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>D. Buckingham,</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Councillors.</item>
                  <item>D. <hi>Monmouth,</hi> General.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Grey,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Gerrard,</hi> and his Son,</item>
                        <item>Sir <hi>Tho. Armſtrong,</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Lieutenant Generals.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Waller</hi> to be <hi>Major Generals.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> 
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Field, and other Officers,</hi> moſt of them meet at the ſeveral Clubs, together with ſome that are in the Country.</p>
            <p>The conſiderable Parties would come from His Majeſties horſe and foot Guards, to joyn them when occaſion ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſop,</hi> and <hi>Gooding</hi> promiſe to introduce me to Lord <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> to be employ'd as a ſpie, and to have the promiſe for a Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>That only the conſent of Sir <hi>J. P. D. B.</hi> Sir <hi>W. W.</hi> Sir <hi>R.P.</hi> was wanting to give the ſtroke, but if they would not comply, it ſhould be done otherwiſe as at the Parliaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53111:16"/>A Parchment was ſeen in the hands of Captain <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Bed.</hi> on <hi>Munday,</hi> the 22d. of <hi>Sept.</hi> 79. which was written on in indented letters. <hi>Theſe are to Authorize &amp;c.</hi> And thirteen Label ſeals to it. <hi>This at Bloods Club.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the ſame night was a ſecret Cabal held at <hi>Bloods</hi> houſe.</p>
            <p>The next being <hi>Tueſday</hi> night was one at Sir, <hi>W.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gooding</hi> told me a Corporal of his acquaintance was going to be liſted, to diſcipline men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> the 19 of <hi>September,</hi> a perſon was ſent from <hi>Bloods</hi> Club to <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> about weighty buſineſs, and is not yet returned, which cauſes ſome fear of miſcarriage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 30th. the Meſſenger returned from <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> who ſaid he had finiſht the buſineſs he went about, and that all that part of the Country, was in good readineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday,</hi> the 5th. of <hi>October,</hi> a Cabalmet at <hi>Wallers</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult about the affaires of other Counties: but particularly for the preſent, the County of <hi>Dorſet, Devon, and Cornwal,</hi> and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto two perſons were ſent away with great Pacquets, and in one of them were divers Papers like printed warrants, and names, and ſeals to the ſame, but the perſon who ſaw them could not come to read one; <hi>my Author is Alſop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Munday,</hi> the 7th. a Cabal met at <hi>Wallers</hi> in order to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of divers perſons into the North, and to <hi>York</hi> City to a Club there at one <hi>Lees</hi> houſe a Tallow-Chandler. Theſe go into ſome part of <hi>Scotland</hi> too, before they return, and yet are obliged to return before the 30th. of this Month.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>W.W.</hi> promiſe to <hi>B.</hi> for a Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Lord <hi>S.</hi> promiſe of a Commiſſion to <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goodings</hi> promiſe to me of the liſt of 5000. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 9. <hi>Brown</hi> produced a paper to the company, who all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of it, but eſpecially one <hi>Deſny,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Curſed be the man whoſe mind is not ſuitable to this Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>Maſon</hi> at the ſame place ſaid after ſome diſcourſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, <hi>that all within</hi> 20 <hi>miles round London, were raedy to ſtrike,</hi> whenſoever they ſhould be commanded, and that againſt the Kings Intereſt too: and ſaid it was not the French Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Invaſion, ſhould put them in fear of any Army the King now had, or could raiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53111:16"/>'Tis alſo Reſolved, that when any Commiſſions are given out for the Raiſing an Army for the King, that ſome of the Faction ſhall privately put in for Employs, in order to the better ſerving that Party by the corrupting His Majeſties Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. <hi>Witt. Curtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 15th. of <hi>Octob.</hi> I was with Lord <hi>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday,</hi> 19. <hi>B.</hi> told me Sir <hi>W.W.</hi> ſaid he had 300 Horſe at his command to oppoſe an Army that the <hi>D.</hi> and <hi>Lauderdale</hi> were going to raiſe in the North; and that if they made not too much haſte, he ſhould have more.</p>
            <p>This is the true Copy of the Paper-book found in the Meal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tub, which being ſince well ſifted to the Bran, appears to be <hi>a Tale of a Tub.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that the Reader may be more fully ſatisfied of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Informations given in to the King, I ſhall give him the true Copy of a Letter ſent by Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi> to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR, May it pleaſe your moſt Sacred Majeſty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ON</hi> Friday <hi>the 26th. of this Inſtant</hi> Septemb. was ſeen by a perſon whom I employ, in the hand of one <hi>England,</hi> a Paper like a Liſt of mens Names, and a Parchment in the likeneſs of a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, with thirteen Label-ſeals, and as many Names thereto, and at the top, was in great Indenture Letters <hi>(viz.) Theſe are to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I my ſelf was inform'd, that a Corporal now in your Majeſties Foot-Guards, was to be ſent into the North to diſcipline a conſiderable number of Men: My Author for this was one <hi>Gooding,</hi> a Nonconformiſt Parſon.</p>
                  <p>Friday <hi>the 26th.</hi> was a perſon ſent with a Packet, very conſiderable, (ſuppos'd to be ſo by my friend who ſaw the outſide thereof) to <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton:</hi> the ſaid perſon is not yet returned, nor to be heard of, which much amazes the gang he was ſent by, and at preſent puts a ſtop to their Party.</p>
                  <p>It was ſpoken publickly in a Club, That all things were in a ready po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53111:17"/>and they only expect your Majeſties Command to make the on-ſet; but if that be not, 'tis deſigned at the ſitting of the Parliament, if your Majeſty anſwer not their expectation.</p>
                  <p>I have alſo diſcovered a great Correſpondence between the ſame Party and the Dutch; and believe at your Majeſties return to give a good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the ſame by Gods help; till which time I ſhall uſe my utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make my ſelf</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Faithful and Obedient Subject <hi>Willoughby,</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe were the great Informations given in againſt the poor Proteſtants; the Reſult of all the Wit of the Popiſh Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; a Project ſo full of Self-inconſiſtencies; this His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty muſt look through, and through it, at the firſt glance of his Eye, only his Wiſdom might let them play with their own Fancies, till they were ſnared in their own Nets. In the Meal-Tub Information, it was the <hi>22th. of September that the Parchment was ſeen in Captain</hi> Englands <hi>hands;</hi> but in Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi>'s Letter to His Majeſty it was <hi>Septemb. the</hi> 26th. Again, in the Meal-tub Paper, it was <hi>Friday the</hi> 19th. <hi>of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember that the Meſſenger was ſent to</hi> Huntingdon; but in this Letter to His Majeſty it was ſaid <hi>Friday the</hi> 26th. <hi>a whole week later:</hi> But let them ſtudy at their leiſure to reconcile Contradictions.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Matters being thus laid, and His Majeſty now return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>London,</hi> by the <hi>Lords Order,</hi> he <hi>muſt go with another Story to the King, but much what of the ſame tendency; and by Mr.</hi> Chif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finch<hi>'s means, Mr.</hi> Willoughy <hi>is brought to ſpeak with His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty:</hi> An Account of which being given to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> and what His Majeſty ſaid, her Ladyſhip anſwered, <hi>he could carry ſomething of moment, but that till he heard further from her, he was commanded to be diligent to enquire after one Coll.</hi> Mansfield, <hi>which I eaſily did</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and ſent word by Madam</hi> Cellier <hi>to the Tower, where he lodge; upon which</hi> I <hi>received Orders from the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53111:17"/>Lady</hi> Powis <hi>to be at home in the Afternoon, and ſhe would come to ſhe did ſo, and commanded me to go to Confeſsion, and receive the Sacrament. After ſome time the aforeſaid Lady ſaid</hi> (after ſome diſcourſe) <hi>will you take theſe Papers, and privately put them into ſome of his Cloaths, or into his Trunks, or any where about his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber?</hi> I anſwered, <hi>I could not do that, becauſe I knew him not;</hi> then ſhe told me, <hi>I muſt go and pretend to ſome acquaintance, and take him to a Tavern, and drink hard, and ſo convey them into his Cloaths, and immediately cry out, he had ſpoken</hi> Treaſon, <hi>and call the Conſtable, and cauſe him to be apprehended and ſearched.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in order to Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s being acquainted with Coll. <hi>Mansfield</hi> (for ſo the Counteſs miſtook his Name) he was adviſed to take lodgings near him, and inſinuate himſelf into his acquaintance, and therewith the Lady <hi>gives him</hi> 15 <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and a list of Names, whereof one was written with her Ladiſhips own hand.</hi> Theſe ſhe deſired might be tranſcribed, and when Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> officiouſly offer'd his ſervice; ſhe replied, <hi>O no! the King having ſome remarks already written with your hand, will know your hand again, for theſe muſt be ſhewed to the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil;</hi> and therefore ſends him to a Scrivener that lives over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Somerſet-houſe</hi> who copied them out; and then he brings them to Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> and ſhewed them to her, who with Mrs. <hi>Webb</hi> adviſed him to proceed, and wiſhed him good ſucceſs, and both warranted him <hi>he ſhould be well rewarded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> goes now into <hi>Axe-Yard,</hi> to the Collonel's Lodgings, and there views the Rooms, and found all things look very hopefully towards the executing his deſign; but at that time he took no Lodgings there, but ſent an Account to the Tower how things ſtood, and then went in perſon (as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes) to the Lord <hi>Peterborough,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> and told them the Deſign, as he was ordered by the Lady <hi>(Powis)</hi> who well approved of it.</p>
            <p>At his Return to his own Lodgings he meets with a Letter from the Lady, whereby he is ordered to proceed forthwith, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53111:18"/>which he obeys, and preſently goes and takes the Lodgings, and puts the fatal Papers behind the Bed, and came away, and ſends word to the Lords in the Tower what he had done: then the perſons concerned commended him, and conſult one another by Letters, and gave him order to Acquaint His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to go to Mr. <hi>Secretary Coventry,</hi> and make <hi>Affidavit,</hi> what he had ſeen in the Collonel's Chamber; but Mr. <hi>VVillough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> or <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> fearing, it ſeems, from ſome jealouſies he had, to be proved a perjured perſon, was reſolved to let it fall, till they ſent word he muſt now go forwards, and he ſhould be well provided for: And theſe heads of the Conſpiracy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him by a Letter to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> to go to ſome Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe, and inform them of ſome prohibited goods, which were in Collonel <hi>Mansfield</hi>'s Chamber, which he did, and brought them in purſuance of that ſearch to detect the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary treaſonable Papers conveyed behind the Bed.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi> having proceeded thus far, yet appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended himſelf within reach of danger, and therefore fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of being ſuſpected, as ſoon as the Officers had ſeized the Papers, and carried them to the Cuſtom-houſe, he withdraws to ſend word to the Tower that the Papers were ſeized: And the Lords there were not without apprehenſions that the Papers might be conveyed away; and therefore immediately ſend him word, to acquaint His Majeſty how the Papers were ſeized, who ſends Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> to Mr. <hi>Secretary Coventry,</hi> that he ſhould come forthwith to <hi>VVhitehall;</hi> but in the mean time Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> not knowing what further to ſay when he ſhould attend the King, goes home to adviſe with Madam <hi>Cellier,</hi> where not long after he was apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the Juſtice taking Bail, and ordering him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Council next morning, the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> meets him in the Stone-Gallery, encourages him to ſtand faſt, aſſuring him, that if he were committed, he ſhould be brought off, and want for nothing. That night he ſtood again upon his Bail, and was ordered to attend the Council next day at three a clock, which gave him a convenient time to be better inſtructed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53111:18"/>And full inſtructions he received the next day from the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> her own hand, as ſhe met him in the ſtone Gallery, with a <hi>ſtrict charge</hi> to ſtand faſt, <hi>which he reſolved and promiſed to do.</hi> Theſe Inſtructions he tranſcribed whilſt in the Meſſengers hands, and kept cloſe to them in his pleading before the Council, as by comparing his Defence with his Inſtructions will evidently appear, a Copy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at the concluſion of this Paragraph ſhall be preſented to the Reader.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding whatever defence he could make, and though according to the charge of Mr. <hi>Sharp his ghoſtly Father,</hi> he ſtoutly denied all that was alledged againſt him before the Council; yet was he committed to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate; the place</hi> (as he obſerves) <hi>from whence they had fetch'd out at firſt, and now by theſe intrigues had returned him back thither at laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Priſon Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ſends her Maid with that old repeated charge <hi>To ſtand faſt;</hi> promiſing him he ſhould want for nothing; and encouraging him to hope he ſhould be removed to the <hi>Kings-bench;</hi> and the ſame time ſhe ſends him <hi>one Guinney, and twenty ſhillings in ſilver,</hi> and a of paper filled with Croſſes, and by the hand of Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> this grave ſentence written, <hi>I will never change:</hi> but Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> was her ſelf it ſeems got into priſon too; and not knowing but that if Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> ſhould find cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage enough to <hi>ſtand faſt</hi> and reſolute, as ſhe enjoined him, yet the wiſdom of the Council might poſſibly entrap them in ſome contradictions; ſhe ſends therefore her ſervant a ſecond time with a Letter of advice to him, which ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this purpoſe: <hi>I am in cuſtody; and if examin'd how I came to know you, will declare I employ'd you to gather in deſperate debts; I would have you ſay the ſame if you be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd; and ſay alſo that it was you that ſent me to the Lord</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and I will ſay ſo too; for this cannot worſt you.</hi> And with this Letter ſhe ſent him their Debt-books, that he might from thence be inſtructed to make his tale good.</p>
            <q> 
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53111:19"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="instructions">
                        <head>A true Copy of the Inſtructions ſent to Mr. <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> by the hands of the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> teaching him how to make his Defence before the Council, and anſwer all Objections.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>FIrſt,</hi> I am ſuſpected to have put the Letters behind the bed, when I went to take the rooms.</p>
                        <p>The improbability of that is plain: for I neither knew what Room <hi>Manſell</hi> would lye in, nor if I my ſelf ſhould be entertained there.</p>
                        <p>But when I had been told which Rooms were to be let, it plainly appears I did not deſire <hi>Manſell</hi> ſhould out of his Lodging to give me place.</p>
                        <p>And after I had taken the Lodgings, they cannot prove that I was any more in <hi>Manſell</hi>'s Lodgings till the ſearch was made.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly, Stretch</hi> ſwears, I at the ſame time that he was ſearching, went round the bed, and he believes I then put them there, for the reaſon that I firſt eſpied the papers.</p>
                        <p>But 'tis ſtrange that the Miſtreſſes Brother, one Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger more, and others in the room, at the ſame time, could not ſee me go round the bed as well as <hi>Stretch.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This is twice I am ſuſpected, for that he alſo ſwears I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the Letters to be treaſonable papers before I ſee the inſide of any one; and that he never read any Letter to me.</p>
                        <p>To prove he did, let Mr. <hi>Bedford</hi> be examined: I alſo deſired them to ſeize all the reſt of his Letters and Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, which were of great conſequence, and a conſiderable number of both, and bring them immediately to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Council, whither I went expecting to find them; but it ſeems they were carried to the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſent to Juſtice <hi>Warcup,</hi> when five or ſix of the Letters found behind the bed, had been taken out, and all the Pamphlets, and two or three hundred Letters more, and <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53111:19"/>a Parchment or two with great ſeals to them, were returned to Mr. <hi>Manſell</hi> again, and only ſuch as were thought fit to be withſtood by him, here produced.</p>
                        <p>To teſtifie the other Letters, Mr. <hi>Bedford.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I alſo deſire to know what time, and where the Writings were delivered to him again, and why they were not all produced, as well as thoſe that are?</p>
                        <p>And why they were not from that time forthwith by him carried before ſome Secretary of State to peruſe?</p>
                        <p>And by what power he could examine the Boy, and give him Wine?</p>
                        <p>And why the Boy was threatned to be ſent to <hi>Bridewell,</hi> or with a Conſtable?</p>
                        <p>And why he was afterwards called good Boy, and told he was the prettieſt Boy they ever ſee?</p>
                        <p>Now if the Boy (who if asked can declare I never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtructed him in the leaſt tittle) would not tell the truth (as they call it) without being thus prompted and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I humbly conceive little credit can be given to what he ſays; but if it were truth, and had come freely from him (as it did not) he is not of age to underſtand an Oath.</p>
                        <p>Pray let Mr. <hi>Bedford</hi> be asked if this <hi>Manſell</hi> did not at any time uſe to go to a Factious Club in <hi>Weſtminſter-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket;</hi> or if he did not bring a ſcandalous Pamphlet, titled, <hi>The Word out of doors,</hi> and there applaud the ſame.</p>
                        <p>I deſire to know if he does not know Captain <hi>Brown,</hi> Mr. <hi>Diſney,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hamey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> Mr. <hi>Kenniſton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Philips,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> Mr. <hi>Murray,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pemberton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker,</hi> and many of the Faction about the Town? and if he had not frequented their Meetings? If he has, then he may juſtly be ſuſpected; for theſe are moſt notorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt the Faction, who cannot love or endure to hear any ſpeak well of His Majeſty, or the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>Now I would fain know how <hi>Doyley</hi> could be ſo well acquainted with me, to know my name to be any other but <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and by what power he examined the Boy? and <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53111:20"/>when he ſee me at the Tower? and how often?</p>
                        <p>And how long he has had the counterfeit Guinney, and from whom? And how he came to attend the Council juſt that morning I was there? And if I miſtake not, he has ſince declared, If I had not ſpoke to him, he would have ſaid nothing to me: Why then ſhould Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> now pretend to produce the counterfeit Guinney againſt me?</p>
                        <p>Or, why not when he ſee me in the <hi>Tower,</hi> or ſince? for he has met me divers times in the ſtreets: Can this appear to be any more than envy in the higheſt, or ſome mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of <hi>Manſell,</hi> or his Intereſt, to invalidate my teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and ſtrengthen their deſign?</p>
                        <p>Now, my Lords, I humbly conceive, that the Guinney being counterfeit, is Treaſon; and if Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> knew me the author of it, it muſt alſo be Treaſon in him for concealing it thus long: for though he may have His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Commiſſion to apprehend ſuch, he is not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal, compound, or ſmuther any ſuch crime, after twenty four hours, of himſelf, which he hath done in this.</p>
                        <p>He alſo went divers times to one <hi>William Leigh,</hi> a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in <hi>Newgate</hi> (and by him apprehended for clipping and coining) and offer'd to ſue out his pardon for ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore pounds, and he not be indicted for the crime; which had been done, had not ſome friend prevented, and ſo he would have done with divers others which were tryed in <hi>York-ſhire.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>By all matters and things it's clear as the Sun, they have ſtir'd up all the firebrands could be thought of, to burn me with: but I know I am before a Juſt and Wiſe King, whom I humbly implore to inſpect and conſider my honeſt endeavours to do your Majeſty ſervice.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Having given the Reader the Copy of his Inſtructions, I now proceed to Col. <hi>Manſell</hi>'s part of the ſtory more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely; where we ſhall ſee how exactly Mr. <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> kept to them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53111:20"/>
            <head>The true manner of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s leaving the Treaſonable Papers in the Lodgings of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>R. Manſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>ON <hi>Wedneſday October</hi> 15. 1679, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the feigned name of Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> (who the ſame day under the borrowed name of Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> had attempted the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>) came to the houſe of Mr. <hi>Alexauder Harris</hi> in <hi>Axe-yard</hi> in <hi>Kingſtreet Weſtminſter,</hi> and enquired for Lodgings; but becauſe nothing would pleaſe him but the two rooms of one floor, and one pair of ſtairs high, of which the room forward was already di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed of, and of which the Gentleman in poſſeſſion could not be diſpoſſeſs'd without his conſent, which at that time could not through his abſence be deſired, Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> for that time departed.</p>
               <p>He had then many Irons in the fire, and ſome of them if he were not very nimble, would cool; for he was not to take a ſtep without advice from his great Maſters; which having gotten, he returns, and on <hi>Friday Octob.</hi> 17. drives a bargain at firſt word for thoſe two rooms, giving at firſt word whatever the Gentlewoman of the houſe asked; for a little money muſt not break the ſquares in an affair of this weight; Col. <hi>Manſells</hi> favour being obtained to remove one pair of ſtairs higher forward, that he might not hinder the houſe of ſo beneficial a Lodger as Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> promiſed to be. When he came this day, the Gentlewoman of the houſe being abroad, he was conducted by a kinſwoman in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the room whither the Colonel was to remove, and there left to his own thoughts for about half an hour; in which time, it now appears by his own confeſſion that he fixed the Troubleſome and Treaſonable Papers behind the beds head. He promiſed to come that night with his friend, for whom he pretended to have taken the other room; but having advice to give what he had done, and advice to take how further to proceed, he came not till the next day, <hi>Saturday Octob.</hi> 18. when he enquired whether his Trunks were <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53111:21"/>come? but they had heard of none. After much imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent diſcourſe, he departs a ſecond time, promiſing to come to take poſſeſſion the next night, for that night he could not, his friend being out of Town; yet he failed then alſo; but on <hi>Monday Octob.</hi> 20. he viſited them, with ſhort inquiries whether his Trunks were come; and being anſwered nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, he once more diſappears. On <hi>Tueſday</hi> night, having by that time gotten full inſtructions how to proceed, about ten of the clock at night he appears with one Captain <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in his company, who as he told the houſe, was that Friend for whom he had taken the other Lodging; and both lay in one bed in the room one pair of ſtairs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> between ſeven or eight a clock in the morning, Col. <hi>Manſell</hi> being gone out about his occaſions, came two Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe, with a Conſtable, to ſearch for prohibited or uncuſtomed Goods: They firſt went into the Chamber where Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> and his friend lay, and from thence conducted by Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> into the Colonels Chamber, where they made a thorough ſearch, breaking open the Colonels Trunks and Boxes, examining the Bed-clothes, and at laſt after intimation given by Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> they proceeded to remove the Bed, which they did three foot from the Wall, but could find nothing, till Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> went behind it, and there eſpied a Packet of papers <hi>(he that hides, can find)</hi> and preſently asks, <hi>What's that there?</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> with great haſte ſnatches a paper out of the Officers hand, and ere he could have time to read the contents, cryed out, <hi>Here's Treaſon.</hi> It was a liſt of names, ſome at length, others only with the initial letters. The ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher opening another paper, and beginning to read, Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> again cryes out, <hi>There's Treaſon againſt His Majeſty,</hi> and therefore the papers (and the perſon upon whom they were found, had he been preſent) ought to be ſecured. The Officers knowing better what belong to their own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, than that of a Juſtice of the Peace, take theſe papers, and carried them not to a Secretary of State (as Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> charged them) but to their own Maſters at the Cuſtom-houſe, permitting a Gentlewoman there preſent, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53111:21"/>of Mrs. <hi>Harris,</hi> to go along with them.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Harris</hi> being in a great perplexity at this unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſurprizing ſeizure; yet loſt not the uſe of her pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but ſends her brother, and preſently follows her ſelf, to find out the Colonel at the ſign of the Cat in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, where the Colonel left word at his going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, he might be ſpoke with at eleven of the clock; and ſhe met him juſt going to the deſigned place.</p>
               <p>She relates him (all amazed) the whole of this affair; and out of her too great care for his ſafety, adviſed him to take Lodgings in the City, promiſing to convey to him the reſt of his goods. But the Colonels Innocency and Courage would not ſuffer him to follow the well-meant, but really ill counſel; for then his withdrawing had been a flight, his flight had proved his guilt, and his perſonal guilt had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved hundreds of innocent perſons with him in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. He therefore anſwers, That he was not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to himſelf of any Treaſonable Deſigns, and therefore would go to the Cuſtom-houſe to know by what authority his Box was ſeized, and what was become of theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed papers. Whither immediately he went.</p>
               <p>There he meets with one Mr. <hi>Boſtock</hi> that had ſearcht his Chamber; who informed him, That one Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> the Monday before, came and informed of 2000 <abbr>l.</abbr> worth of <hi>Flanders</hi> ſilver and gold Lace, ſtowed in ſuch a place; and this was the Contrivance of Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> own Mother-wit, who when Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was at a loſs how to proceed with the Colonel when he had fixt the Papers behind his bed, waving the old thredbare artifice of ſearching for arms, adviſed to make the diſcovery by the Officers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom-houſe. But here Colonel <hi>Manſell</hi> underſtands that his Papers were all returned, all his own, and more than his own, the Treaſonable ones to boot; and accordingly at his return he finds the Box reſtored, and the Papers lying on the Dreſſer, ſuperſcribed by the Maſter of the houſe, <hi>For Col. Manſell.</hi> Theſe Papers he opens in the preſence of Mr. <hi>Harris,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Harris,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Orde;</hi> deſiring them to take notice of them and their number, which was Nine; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, for more caution, Mr. <hi>Harris</hi> to put his mark on them,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53111:22"/>that he might more certainly know, and confidently own them to be the ſame when they ſhould come to be examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before Authority; which he reſolved they ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be. In order to which, he carries them with him to adviſe with a Friend what to do in the caſe. Whoſe ready advice was, To go forthwith to a Secretary of State. This he endeavoured, but not finding my Lord <hi>Sunderland</hi> or any of his Clerks at the Office, nor Mr. Secretary <hi>Coventry</hi> or his Clerks in their Office, the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Capel</hi> being alſo from home; he addreſt himſelf to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentleman, <hi>Mr. Juſtice Warcup,</hi> to whom he opened the whole affair; and having got together the Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe, the Maſter and Miſtreſs of the Colonels Lodgings, and whatever other Evidence they then had; he was pleaſed to take their Depoſitions: Upon the whole matter it appeared to him, That it was a malicious deſign of this <hi>Mr. Thomas,</hi> and therefore granted out a Warrant for his apprehenſion; which being delivered to a Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, this vvorthy Gentleman vvent along vvith him to <hi>Mr. Celliers,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Merchant, and a Papiſt, vvhere <hi>Mr. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> now, and the St. <hi>Omers</hi> Boys formerly had lodged; where the Juſtice, Conſtable, and Warrant found him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>Mr. Willoughby</hi> underſtood their errand, he cryed out, <hi>Oh! this is Mr. Manſell's doing! What has he cryed Whore firſt! but I have been this day with the King my ſelf, and with Mr. Secretary</hi> Coventry, <hi>and have acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with the buſineſs; ſo that I ſuppoſe there will be ſome to enquire for him ere his return. Col. Warcup</hi> anſwer'd him, <hi>That if he found Sureties to appear at the Council-board next morning by nine of the Clock, he ſhould at preſent give him no further trouble.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi> the <hi>Frtnch</hi> Merchant, and an Apothecary entring into Recognizance for that end, he was bailed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday Octob.</hi> 23. forenoon. That morning as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned attended the Council in the Lobby, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> met with a very unhappy rencounter; who as he was going down the ſtairs of the Lobby, met with one Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> an Officer belonging to the Mint, who had formerly known and proſecuted one Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> for diſpoſing of <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53111:22"/>falſe <hi>Guinnies,</hi> and Clipping of Money: Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> eſpying him, and being perhaps Conſcious of his former Crimes, began to Curſe without any Provocation, <hi>Damn and Sink him!</hi> what had <hi>Doyley to ſay to him?</hi> Threatning, that if he had him out of the Court, he would run him through; and that when ever he met him in Convenient place, he would be Revenged of him: Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> was indeed Surpriſed at ſuch courſe Language; and the more, becauſe he knew a perſon of his Character could not have any Affairs that were good there.</p>
               <p>But my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>North</hi> paſſing by towards the Council, and Over-hearing the Repartees, Mr. <hi>Doy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> made Application to his Lordſhip; and preſently Mr. Juſtice <hi>Warcup</hi> was ſent for in, and Ordered to take the Information of Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> with order to a Meſſenger to take Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> into Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: Mr. Juſtice <hi>Warcup</hi> directs the meſſenger to take him to the Kings-head Tavern; whither as ſoon as the Council was riſen, he promiſed to come: and during the ſtay there, Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> (who had his Boy in Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to wait on him, for his trade would have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it) Writes a Note, and directs it to Mris. <hi>Cellier,</hi> to this purpoſe; <hi>That ſhe ſhould go to the Lord, and Lady</hi> Powis, <hi>and acquaint them that he was taken up, for the old buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they knew of.</hi> This Note the Meſſenger would not ſuffer the Boy to Carry till he read the Contents of it, and then he diſmiſt him, who carried according to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>This morning, the Council had the Affair of Mr. <hi>Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> before them, ſo that when Collonel <hi>Warcup</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in his Examinations taken the day before, about Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> they were all Commanded to appear in the afternoon at four of the Clock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> Oct. 23. <hi>Afternoon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was firſt call'd in, and preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, Collonel <hi>Manſell</hi> was called in, to whom the <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> was pleas'd to ſay: <hi>What Correſpondencies are theſe you hold? Here are Papers of dangerous Conſequence, ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53111:23"/>the Levying of Men, and raiſing Rebellion againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty! Here is alſo a Liſt of mens Names whom you have En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſted.</hi> The Collonell humbly replied, that <hi>he knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thoſe Letters, and Papers; neither had he, or did, or ever would hold any Treaſonable Correſpondence with any perſon living.</hi> He humbly pray'd the Favour of the Honourable Board, that he might be permitted to give an account how he came by the ſight of thoſe Papers, and then he did not Queſtion but he ſhould make it appear, that thoſe Papers were deſignedly, and maliciouſly brought into his Chamber by Mr. <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the Collonel gave to their Lordſhips, a full and clear, yet Conciſe Account of what he knew, or had been informed in, by Perſons of the Family where he Lodged, and the Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe: and being Commanded to call in his Witneſſes, he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly did ſo</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Alexander Harris</hi> was firſt Sworn, who Witneſſed, that the Papers before that Honourable Board, were the ſame left at his houſe for Collonel <hi>Manſel,</hi> by the Officer of the Cuſtom-houſe.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Stretch,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Boſtock,</hi> were next Sworn, who depoſed amongſt other matters, That Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> having informed them of certain Prohibited Goods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed in <hi>Ax-Yard,</hi> appointed them to come to him at Mr. <hi>Celliers</hi> Houſe in <hi>Arundel</hi>-Buildings the laſt Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; Whither being come, in order to the Search and Seizure, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> told them he was not yet Ready, having not yet Lodged at his New Quarters; but would not Fail to be there that preſent Night, and therefore appointed them to come thither on Wedneſday Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. That at the time prefixt they came, and found Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> with his Friend in their Chamber; that Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> took him aſide, and Whiſpered to him, that the Goods were in the Room above-head, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to charge himſelf to Aſſiſt them: That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a narrow Search, finding no ſuch Goods as were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> pointed towards the Bed, which they drew out Three Foot from the Wall, and Searched with all Exactneſs; but ſtill Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> 
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53111:23"/>pointing to the Beds-head, Mr. <hi>Stretch</hi> went once more behind the Bed, with a Candle; but with the ſame Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. At laſt Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> going behind the Beds-head alone, call'd to the Officers; <hi>What's that hangs there? Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them a Packet of Papers, pinned to the Beds-Head.</hi> The Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer taking them down, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſnatch't one of them out of his Hand; and ere he could Read any thing, cryed out, <hi>Here is Treaſon!</hi> The Officer taking another Paper, and reading it, there were Words to this Purpoſe: <hi>I wonder at your Delay, and that the Four Lords have left Us; for now the Old</hi> tyrant <hi>has declar'd himſelf a</hi> Papiſt! At which Words, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> cry'd out; <hi>Ay, That's the</hi> King! <hi>That's the</hi> King, <hi>he means! Did not I tell you, theſe were Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Papers? and that you ought to Secure them, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon too, if he had been here; and carry them either before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or a Secretary of State?</hi> Mr. <hi>Stretch</hi> alſo ſwears, That theſe were the ſame Papers, that were taken from behind the Beds-head; and that he did verily believe, they were put there by Mr. <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was now late; and the Council riſing, ordered Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> to be Committed to a Meſſenger; and Collonel <hi>Manſel,</hi> with his Witneſſes, to appear the next Day, at <hi>Four</hi> of the Clock in the Afternoon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Fryday,</hi> Octob. 24. <hi>Afternoon, at the Council-Board.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Council being met, Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi> put in his Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition, <hi>That the reſt of his Witneſſes might be heard:</hi> Upon which His Majeſty was pleaſed to order, That the Cauſe ſhould be heard the next Council-Day.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> moved, that till that time, he might ſtand upon Bail; but an Order was granted, That he ſhould remain in the Meſſenger's Cuſtody, as before: With which Order, the Meſſenger acquainted him very Civilly: But he ſtorm'd, and ſwore, <hi>He was confident, there was no ſuch Order; for he knew, there were thoſe within, that would not ſuffer him to be ſo treated.</hi> But the Meſſenger inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Order, and demanded his Sword; which he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to deliver to him, but to another Meſſenger. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was ſafely Conducted to the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger's Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:53111:24"/>The Council that Night, after a ſhort Receſs, ſate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; And his Majeſty was gratiouſly pleaſed, to appoint the Collonel's Affair to be heard on <hi>Monday</hi> following, at <hi>Four</hi> in the Afternoon: And then a Motion he made, That Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi> ſhould alſo be Committed; The Right Honourable, the <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> oppoſed the Motion, and ſo it fell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> Octob. 27, 1679. <hi>At the Council-Board.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ABout Five or Six of the Clock, in the Afternoon, the Collonel, and Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> were call'd in; where, after a ſhort Repetion of the Charge againſt the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, imployed in the Papers, he prepared to make his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> having received Inſtructions freſh out of the Mint, in the <hi>Tower,</hi> addreſſed himſelf to his Majeſty, with a peculiar Confidence; affirming, That there were Sixteen of theſe Papers found in his Chamber; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he deſired to know, what was become of all the reſt? As alſo, of the Box of Treaſonable Printed Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and Two or Three hundred Letters? Adding, that <hi>Manſel</hi> had got together a Company of Witneſſes, to diſparage the <hi>King</hi>'s Evidence, and to palliate his own Treaſonable Practiſes: And deſired, he might have the Leave to ask the Collonel ſome Queſtions.</p>
               <p>It was granted; and Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> proceeded: <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did not the Collonel frequent the</hi> Angel Clubb, <hi>behind the Exchange, and divers others in the City? Whether he did not keep a Clubb of his own, at one</hi> Street's, <hi>a Tallow-Chandler's Houſe, in the Market-place,</hi> Weſtminſter? <hi>Whether he did not know one</hi> Diſney, Grange, England, L'iſle, <hi>and one Capt.</hi> Brown? Whether he did not bring into his Clubb one Night, a ſcandalous Pamphlet, called, A Word without Doors; <hi>and there publickly read it? And afterwards, uſed Treaſonable Words againſt his</hi> R. Highneſs? The Collonel owned, that he knew many of the Gentlemen by him mentioned; but that they were all very honeſt Gentlemen, and Loyal Subjects; and all of them Inhabitants of <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> ſaving only Capt. <hi>Brown;</hi> who had been Lieutenant to Major <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Troop of <pb n="37" facs="tcp:53111:24"/>Horſe, in his <hi>R. Highneſſes</hi> Regiment: But all Treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diſcourſes with them, or any other, he utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avowed; and was thereupon commanded to call the reſt of his Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Harris,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Harris,</hi> firſt appear'd; who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, as before, That the Number of the Papers (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi>'s Allegation) were not <hi>Sixteen,</hi> but <hi>Nine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Boſtock</hi> confirm'd the ſame; and further, That thoſe Papers, then before the Honorable-Board, were the ſame Papers found behind the Beds-head; And that he did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe, Mr. <hi>VVillonghby</hi> had placed them there.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Stretch</hi> being Sick, appear'd not; but his Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were read, tending to the ſame Effect.</p>
               <p>Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi> then produced a Record, to prove, That Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi> had been Indicted, at an Aſſize held at <hi>Salisbury,</hi> for the County of <hi>VVilts,</hi> in Three Indictments, for uttering Counterfeit <hi>Guinnties</hi> to three ſeveral Perſons. That upon his Tryal, he confeſſed all the Indictments; and was Fined <hi>Five Pound,</hi> upon each Indictment; and further Sentenced, to ſtand in the <hi>Pillory,</hi> he broke the Goal, ran away, and eſcaped the Execution of the Third.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Preſident,</hi> asked Mr. <hi>VVilloughby, What he Could ſay for himſelf?</hi> VVho denyed, that ever he had been at <hi>Salisbury</hi> in all his Life. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was pleaſed to ask him, VVhether he would take his Oath, that he was never there? He readily anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That he would not only take his Oath, but take the <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it alſo! The Lord <hi>Preſident</hi> replyed; <hi>What, will you ſwear againſt a Record? Here's a Record brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you!</hi> Yet he perſiſted to deny, that he was ever there.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Bedford,</hi> his Friend, was then called in; who gave a full Relation, how Mr <hi>Willoughby</hi> came to him on <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> Night before, to deſire him to Lodge with him at his New-Lodgings. He confirm'd the Evidence of Mrs. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and the reſt, as to the manner of Searching the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel's Chamber, and the finding of the Papers: Adding, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:53111:25"/>further; That going to Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Houſe, to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> he told him what an Evil Thing he had done, not only to the Collonel, but himſelf, to ingage him in ſo vile a Buſineſs, which now was ſo clearly laid open: And therefore, deſired him to diſcover the whole Truth, and who had Engaged him in it. To which Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> replyed; <hi>Piſh! I doubt not to come off; for the Greateſt Man in</hi> England, <hi>has engaged me in it.</hi> To which Capt. <hi>Bedford</hi> rejoyned, <hi>Whom do you mean,</hi> The King? Ay! ſaid Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> The King! And further; That he underſtood, that Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> held Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> in the <hi>Tower;</hi> and that he had ſeen the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> her Coach, on <hi>Saturday</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſtanding before Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s Lodgings.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> was the next Witneſs call'd in, who Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that he had Proſecuted the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> at two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Seſſions</hi> held in the <hi>Old-Bayley,</hi> for Clipping of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and Vending of Falſe Guinnies. Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Askt <hi>what he could ſay to that?</hi> Anſwered, <hi>That he had been twice there Proſecuted, by the ſaid</hi> Mr. Doyley, <hi>but all was out of pure malice.</hi> He confeſſed that he had been Fined Fifty Pounds for the Firſt Offence; and for the Second, had obtained His Majeſties Gracious Pardon; ſo that he hoped thoſe Matters ſhould not be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred againſt him. The Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> demanding of him, Who had Solicited His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for his Pardon? He Anſwered, Capt. <hi>Richardſon</hi> had put his Name into a Pardon, for which he gave him Three Guinnies.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Richardſon</hi> was then Examin'd, who upon his Oath, Witneſſed, That he had this Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> in his Cuſtody two Seſſions: That the firſt time his Fine was remitted, and he Diſcharged: That the ſecond time, he had put his Name into His Majeſties <hi>Newgate-Pardon;</hi> but that he never received any Guinnies from him, upon ſuch account; and indeed, he believed he was then not worth a Guinney. That he never had a more Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Rogue</hi> in his Cuſtody; who, during the time of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, was alwayes contriving Miſchief, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Diſturbance amongſt the Priſoners. That whilſt he <pb n="39" facs="tcp:53111:25"/>was there, he had practiſed Forgery. That in or about laſt <hi>May,</hi> one Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, whom he had obſerved to come to the Priſon, to Viſit and Relieve the Papiſts then in his Cuſtody, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the account of the late Plot, paid Ten Pounds for the Diſcharge of the ſaid <hi>Willoughby,</hi> rigg'd him out in handſom Apparel, and ſo took him away: Of which he took ſuch particular Notice, That he acquainted Mr. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Warcub</hi> what Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> had done; and that this <hi>Willoughby</hi> was a dangerous Perſon, and deſired him to keep an eye upon him. That he had obſerved the ſaid <hi>Willoughby,</hi> at Sir <hi>George Wakeman's</hi> Tryal, to take Notes, and that he carried them to the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> in the <hi>Tower.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> further Witneſſed, that he ſaw the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> in the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> his Lodgings, the day after the ſaid Tryal; where he heard him villifying Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Captain <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Evidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards, one <hi>Smith</hi> (Mr. <hi>Willoughby's</hi> Foot-Boy) was Examined; who teſtified, That he was ſent with a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and a Note from his Maſter, then in the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger's Hand, to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> deſiring her, to acquaint the ſaid Lord <hi>Powis, That he was taken into Cuſtody for the old buſineſs he knew of.</hi> That for two Months before, he had Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> his houſe in <hi>Queens-Street.</hi> That he had ſeveral times waited on his Maſter to the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> his Lodgings in the <hi>Tower,</hi> which deſcribed to be in the <hi>Mint;</hi> that he had rode behind the Coach, to attend his Maſter thither: That he had ſeveral times carried Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Papers from his Maſter, to the ſaid Lord <hi>Powis;</hi> and brought Anſwers back again to his Maſter. And laſtly, that the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> had ſeveral times been at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Lodgings at Mrs. <hi>Celliers;</hi> and that particularly on Saturday was ſeven-night, the ſaid Lady had been with his Maſter in a <hi>Tower</hi>-Room, in private diſcourſe with him alone, above half an hour.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> was then pleaſed to ask Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby,</hi> whither he had been at the Lord <hi>Shaftsburies.</hi> To which he Anſwered, That he had been ſeveral times with him, and had Diſcourſes with his Lordſhip; ſome of which he there Rehearſed. To which the <hi>Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> 
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:53111:26"/>reply'd, <hi>You are a fine Fellow;</hi> firſt to come to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and there to tell him one Story: Then to the Lord <hi>Powis;</hi> and from thence to my Lord <hi>Shaftsburies;</hi> diſcovering to one, what Diſcourſe you held with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And thus brought one Story to the <hi>Council,</hi> another to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All were commanded to Withdraw, there being no need of the Teſtimony of the reſt of the Collonels Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in a Matter ſo plain and clear. And preſently a Warrant was iſſued out from the Council-Board, to Commit the ſaid Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where he now remains, in his old Quarters; and an Order was given for his Proſecution, to the Mr. Attorney General.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VVedneſday, Octob.</hi> 29. 1679.</head>
               <p>THis day Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> whoſe known Activity, and Zeal for the Service of His Majeſty, and the Proteſtant Religion, did never yet abate; upon ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, thought it Expedient to make a through Search in the Houſe of Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> if perhaps ſomething might be further diſcovered, to give Light to this <hi>Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> where he found that Book, containing the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their deſigned Plot upon the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> which has been already Exemplifyed: And I ſhall only now, give the Copy of the Examination of a Maid-Servant, in the Houſe, which was as follows.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53111:26"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="examination">
                           <head>The Examination of <hi>Anne Blake,</hi> Servant to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> taken on Oath before Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> the 29th. <hi>October,</hi> 1679.</head>
                           <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> delivered into her Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody two parcels of papers, deſiring her to lay them up for her, ſo as they might not be diſcovered, or words to that effect: And that in obedience to her Mistreſſes commands, this Examinant hid one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Papers behind the Pewter in the Kitchin, and the other parcel wrapt up in a ſheet of white paper, amongſt which was a little Paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book tied with red Ribbons, which for the better ſecurity was hid in a Tub of Meal, both which parcels were ſeiſed by Sir <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler:</hi> This Examinant further ſaith, that one <hi>Lane</hi> was this day, at the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Houſe to ſpeak with her; and further this Examinant ſaith not at preſent.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Cap. &amp; Jurat. coram <hi>William Waller.</hi>
                              </signed>
                              <signed>The Mark of <hi>Anne Blake.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> November 1. 1679. <hi>At the Council Chamber in White-Hall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis day the Right Honourable the preſent Lord May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or came to White-Hall, and delivered to His Majeſty, or to His Right Honourable Privy Council the Information of <hi>Thomas Dangerfield</hi> given upon Oath before his Lordſhip, an Extract whereof the Reader hath already had in theſe Papers, as the Particulars referred to the matters diſcourſed of.</p>
               <p>This day alſo ſeveral other Perſons were examined before the Lords of the Council as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suſan Edwards</hi> Servant-Maid to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> who lives in <hi>Arundel</hi>-Street being ſworn, ſays:
<q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="examination">
                              <p>That ſhe carried the two little Papers which were ſhewed her to Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> in <hi>Newgate,</hi> with Twenty Shillings in Silver, <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53111:27"/>and a Guinney; and two Books of Accounts, that he might be perfect in them, and that he looked on the one, and not on the other, and that on <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night laſt, ſhe carried a Meſſage to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby,</hi> from her ſaid Mistreſs. <hi>That her life was in his hands.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>And that the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> had been thrice at Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Houſe in five weeks time, that ſhe had lived there, and that once the ſaid Lady <hi>Powis</hi> had there ſpoken with the ſaid Mr. <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>The Mark of the ſaid <hi>Suſan Edwards.</hi>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q> 
               </p>
               <p>Note, that <hi>the little Papers</hi> mentioned in this Information, are theſe.
<q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="1" type="paper">
                              <head>PAPER I.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>I have ſaid you were taken into my Houſe to get in Desperate Debts:</hi> They bring me to <hi>L. S.</hi> They will ask me who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me to go to him? I will ſay, it was you! It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worſt you.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="2" type="paper">
                              <head>PAPER II.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>I never change.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <figure/>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then was Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> aliàs <hi>Willoughby</hi> further examined, and to his Information before the Lord Mayor he made the following Additions.</p>
               <p>That he had Orders to burn all Papers.</p>
               <p>That all the Lords in the Tower gave him money; One a Guinney; Another Thirty Shillings; One half a Guinney, Others Fifteen or Sixteen Shillings, and deſired him to go to <hi>Turner</hi> to print his Remarks on the Tryals: There were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53111:27"/>who wrote ſhort Hand, and his Remarques were put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theirs.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Lane</hi> lay at <hi>Powis-Houſe,</hi> that Lord adviſed he ſhould be ſent out of the way, for ſaid the Lord <hi>Powis, Oates</hi> ſearches for him, and if he be found at my Houſe, 'twould Ruine us all.</p>
               <p>That Mr. <hi>Stamford,</hi> the <hi>Newburg-Agent,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Celier</hi> walkt together in <hi>Lincolns-inn-Walkes,</hi> to diſcourſe of <hi>Sir George Wakeman</hi>'s eſcape, and that the Informant found them there; and <hi>Stamford</hi> did then ſhew him the Copy of a paper, that had been poſted up at <hi>Sir George Wakeman</hi>'s Door, importing a Menace, <hi>Though he had eſcaped at his Trial.</hi> That he ſaw <hi>Sir George</hi> at <hi>Stamford</hi>'s Houſe, in whoſe own Room he lay; and <hi>Sir George</hi> told him, he was there fain to abſcond for fear. And that he had five hundred Pounds by the Queens order for his Tranſportation.</p>
               <p>That the Informant adviſed him firſt to buy a ſmall Boat for thirty or fourty Pounds, to carry him over: then propoſed the paſſing in one of the <hi>Chaloupes</hi> that uſed to tranſport Wool. That <hi>Sir George</hi> likeing the ſame, went down to Rumney-Marſh, propoſing firſt to go in his Calaſh, and paſs for a French-man, and to take the Informant with him, to return with advice of his Succeſs, but <hi>that</hi> he did not do. That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a Friend in Rumney-Marſh, he writ up for new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe to <hi>Mr. Stamford,</hi> and the Informant hearing thereof, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed that one ſhould go over, and bring a <hi>Chaloup</hi> from <hi>Calice,</hi> to take him in, about ſix miles from <hi>Dover,</hi> which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly took Effect, and he eſcaped to <hi>Newport.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Dormer</hi> did write, <hi>The tranfforming of Traytors into Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs;</hi> That <hi>Gadbury</hi> had writ a Ballad, and ſeveral other Pamphletts.</p>
               <p>That being brought to the <hi>D.</hi> with the Paper he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> the <hi>D.</hi> knew not but that it was real, and ſaid it ſeemed conſiderable.</p>
               <p>That when he firſt returned from the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and gave <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> an account of the diſappointment of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that time, <hi>Mr. Cellier</hi> the Husband was preſent.</p>
               <p>That he had twenty Guinneys from the <hi>D</hi>'s. own Royal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53111:28"/>Hand, when he came at another time to him about the Plot.</p>
               <p>That when he went the ſecond time to the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> if God had not prevented, he had certainly ſtabbed him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have put out the Candle, and under pretence to go down to light it, give it to one of the Servants, and then eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. That his Lordſhip refuſing to ſpeak to him alone, but would have his Servant by, did prevent it.</p>
               <p>He ſays they were angry that he did not make Oath, as <hi>Secretary Coventry</hi> required him, before he would give him a Warrant to Search. And that having pin'd the Letters on <hi>Manſells</hi> Bed, he was ordered by the Lords to go and tell the King thereof, leaſt the Cuſtome-houſe Meſſengers ſhould have concealed them.</p>
               <p>That When he was put into Cuſtody, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ſent preſently to one <hi>Wiggs</hi> an <hi>Attorney</hi> to get him out by <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> bid him follow his Ladies Advice, and conſult with <hi>Turner</hi> his Prieſt, and be ſure what his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy adviſed came from him, and the reſt of the Lords in the Tower.</p>
               <p>He did acknowledg the two Books to be his Hand-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereof one was found in the Meal-Tubb, and ſaid that the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> did declare all thoſe Names with her own Mouth.</p>
               <p>That it was a while after Sr. <hi>George Wakeman</hi> was tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> ſpoke to him in the Lord <hi>Powis</hi>'s Bedchamber about <hi>Killing the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in his ordinary Diſcourſe with Mrs. <hi>Cellier, the King went by the name of the Lady Mary,</hi> and the <hi>Duke by the Name of the Lady Anne,</hi> by agreement between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The ſame Day. Afternoon.</head>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> being ſent for out of the Gate-Houſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd upon the Information of <hi>Willoughby, alias Dangerfeild,</hi> Said.</p>
               <p>That he had for ſome time layn at her Houſe. That ſhe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53111:28"/>having Money to diſtribute at the Priſons. <hi>Willoughby</hi> beg'd there of her, and ſhe collecting three Pound ten Shillings, got him releaſed. That her Husband having great Debts due to him, which looked deſperate, he was imployed in recovery of the ſame, and was to have ſix Shillings in the Pound for what he could get in: and beſides ſhe employed him to Bayl out two or three Priſoners, and that was all which <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> did for her. She denies ſhe paid either twenty Pound or five Pound to get him out. That ſhe never ſent him of any Errand to the Tower.</p>
               <p>That being troubled in her Houſe with Sr. <hi>William Waller</hi>'s Searches, ſhe obtained leave to be at the Lady <hi>Powis</hi>'s Houſe, and <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s Lodgings at the Gote, being troubleſom alſo, he was deſired to go and be at this Examinants Houſe with her Husband. That ſhe never ſaw <hi>Willoughby</hi> and the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> at her Houſe ſpeaking together but once.</p>
               <p>That ſhe did not write to <hi>Willoughby</hi> at his late being in Newgate. But when the Note was ſhew'n her, with a Seal thereon, and ſome Croſſes on the Paper, and theſe words <hi>I never change,</hi> ſhe confeſſed the ſame.</p>
               <p>She pretended Ignorance alſo of another Paper, Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what excuſe Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſhould make, but that alſo being produced, ſhe could not deny that it was her Hand.</p>
               <p>She ſaid ſhe knew not of any Deſign to kill the Lord <hi>Shaftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> but that being told her Houſe was to be ſearcht, ſhe did go to the ſaid Earl on Monday was ſeven-night, and he gave her a kind Anſwer.</p>
               <p>She ſays ſhe never employed <hi>VVilloughby</hi> to draw Articles againſt <hi>Capt. Richardſon,</hi> but yet confeſſed ſhe had ſeen ſome he had drawn himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> was here called in to Confront her, who acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Board: That about the latter end of <hi>March</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> enquiring of Mrs. <hi>VVhite</hi> for a man of deſperate Nature, ſhe named him: That he was firſt employed by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to draw Articles againſt <hi>Cap. Richardſon:</hi> That ſhe ſent by her Maid three Pounds ten Shillings, in order to get him out, and afterwards more, near five Pounds. That he Was arreſted immediately and carried to the Counter; that Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> 
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:53111:29"/>Maid brought him there fifty Shillings, and by the means of <hi>Bannister,</hi> and <hi>Scarlett,</hi> he was removed to the <hi>Kings-Bench:</hi> there he was viſited by her with <hi>Banniſter,</hi> ſhe commended his looks, gave him twenty Shillings, and ſo much afterward <hi>per week.</hi> She ordered him to obſerve the motions of <hi>Strode,</hi> who was there in Priſon, to get thoſe Papers from him, which concerned <hi>Bedlow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he was adviſed by <hi>Hitton</hi> a Preiſt, and others to put Opium in <hi>Strode</hi>'s Drink, in order to ſearch him when faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep for Papers. That <hi>Margaret,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> Maid, brought him <hi>Opium,</hi> from her Son's in Law, <hi>Blaſdell</hi> the Apothecary; that <hi>Mounſon</hi> told him how to uſe it, and to drink Brandy with him in the Cellar, with which <hi>Strode</hi> was only drowzy: that a double Doſe was ſent, which he put for him into a Tankard of ſmall Beer, but it taſting bitter, and he being grown jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, flung Tankard, and all upon the Ground; he ſays alſo, that <hi>Mounſon</hi> gave him leave to drink and be drunk too, as a thing lawful for the good of the Catholick Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>VVilloughby</hi> continued to make a Repetition of his whole Information, wherein Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> was concerned, to which ſhe anſwers by denial of all, falling down on her Knees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching his Majeſty, ſhe might not be tortured; for what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhe ſhould ſay by reaſon of Torture, then that ſhe ſaid at preſent, would be falſe.</p>
               <p>She denies to know any thing of Mr. <hi>Sharp</hi> the Prieſt at <hi>VVild-Houſe,</hi> ſhe owns to have ſeen <hi>VVilloughby</hi> at Maſs, but never at Confeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVilloughby</hi> ſpeaking of his Papers, ſaid; that at Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> he had from the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> the Liſt of the Councellors, and that it came from the Tower: that two thirds of that Book came from the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> and the reſt of the Information from <hi>Capt. Bedford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> Confeſſes at laſt that ſhe hid the Papers in the <hi>Meal-Tub,</hi> but it was his deſire: ſhe acknowledges ſhe did give him caution to call the King <hi>Lady Mary,</hi> and the Duke, the <hi>Lady Anne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſays, that <hi>Knowles</hi> the Prieſt, and <hi>Sharp,</hi> adviſed <pb n="47" facs="tcp:53111:29"/>him, on all occaſions to ſtand firm to what he undertook, and that he would thereby merit Heaven.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> acknowledges the buſineſs of calculating <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi>'s Nativity, but that <hi>Gadburie</hi>'s Papers made it appear that <hi>Willoughby</hi> was to be hanged.</p>
               <p>Then was the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> called in, and examined upon the Information of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> who generally denies all: That ſhe ſent any Letter to <hi>Mounſon</hi> in the King's Bench: That <hi>Margaret</hi> ever carried any Letter from her, to get the Papers out of <hi>Strode</hi>'s hands; or that ſhe gave Mr. <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> thanks for his diligence therein: She denies that ſhe has ſeen him above three times in her life: That ſhe had any Letter from Mr. <hi>Jeane</hi> at <hi>Peterley</hi> by <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet acknowledges ſhe paid Mrs <hi>Cellier</hi> ten Shillings <hi>per week</hi> for Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s Dyet.</p>
               <p>She ſays that his Lodging at <hi>Powis</hi> Houſe, was without her knowledge.</p>
               <p>She owns, that <hi>about a Fortnight ſince ſhe called at Mrs.</hi> Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, <hi>that Mr.</hi> Willoughby <hi>came into the Room where ſhe was, which was the only time ſhe convers'd with him there; and then he told her of ſome Treaſonable Letters hid at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and that the Secretary had refuſed him a Warrant to ſearch for them without making an Affidavit. And that then Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>had adviſed him to make uſe of the Cuſtom-Houſe Officers to ſearch for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She knows nothing of Colonel <hi>Mansfield,</hi> nor of any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers put by <hi>VVilloughby</hi> into his Chamber; nor never gave him fifteen Papers, and a Liſt of Names, nor mentioned any <hi>Scrivener</hi> to him to Copy any Papers: She knows not ſhe had any occaſion to adviſe him to burn his Papers.</p>
               <p>She denies giving him any Inſtructions, and knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his going to the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury.</hi> She ſaw him in the Stone-Gallery, but was not within diſtance of ſpeaking to him: She never heard of any propoſition of <hi>VVilloughby's killing the King:</hi> She abominates the thoughts, or mention of any ſuch wickedneſs; and denies ſhe ever ſpoke of his <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting any opportunity,</hi> as to the King, or the <hi>Lord Shaftsbury,</hi> and denies that <hi>VVilloughby</hi> evet told her he had been <hi>in a Room with the King alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:53111:30"/>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Wood <hi>being examined, ſays,</hi> he knows <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and has ſeen him at Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> and other Places, but never at the Tower: When <hi>Willoughby</hi> dined with the Lord <hi>Powis</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants there, he was from home; he owns he paid Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> twenty pound for the Priſoners; but denies he brought <hi>Willoughby</hi> any money for <hi>Lane.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <head>MIDDLESEX and WESTMINSTER.</head>
                           <head>The Information of Mrs. <hi>Jane Bradley</hi> of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Widow, taken upon Oath, this Firſt Day of <hi>November,</hi> 1679. Before me <hi>Edmond Warcup</hi> Eſquire, one of His Majestie's Justices of the Peace, in the ſaid County, and City.</head>
                           <p>THis Informant ſaith, that upon a Saturday about three weeks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, one <hi>Thomas Curtice</hi> late of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> now in, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London,</hi> came to <hi>Heaven,</hi> where this Informant lives, and as ſhe was lighting him out of doors, he told her, that he heard there were Commiſsions giving forth, and that Mr. <hi>Blood</hi> had the giving them out, and added, that if he could get one of them, it would be Five thouſand pounds in his way; and that this Informant ſhould have part of it; whereupon this Informant asked him, what way he propounded to get one of them? who anſwered by <hi>Captain Brown,</hi> who was one of his Country-men, with whom he was acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Sometime after which, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Curtice,</hi> brought the ſaid <hi>Captain Brown</hi> to the ſame Houſe, but they then diſcourſed nothing of the buſineſs in her hearing: but this Informant did, and doth apprehend, that the ſaid <hi>Curtice</hi> meant that thoſe Commiſsions, were to be given out againſt the King. And ſhe further ſaith, that ſhe ſent for Mr. <hi>Blood,</hi> and acquainted him with the ſaid Diſcourſe, who anſwered 'twas very well done, to tell him thereof, but there was <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53111:30"/>no ſuch thing in being; and about a week after, <hi>Mr. Blood</hi> gave this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant a broad piece of Gold, ſaying you are a poor woman, and directed her to know as much as ſhe could of the matter; and accordingly this Informant did enquire of the ſaid <hi>Curtice</hi> about the 5000 <abbr>l.</abbr> but could get nothing out of him, more than that he was well aſſured of the 5000 <abbr>l.</abbr> And ſhe further ſaith, that <hi>Mr. Blood,</hi> and <hi>Captain Brown,</hi> had been at <hi>Heaven,</hi> together; before that time; and ſhe remembers that ſhe did tell the ſaid <hi>Brown,</hi> that one <hi>Lawton,</hi> one <hi>Pember,</hi> and one <hi>Tresby</hi> were acquainted with the ſaid <hi>Curtice,</hi> and ſhe heard the ſaid <hi>Lawton,</hi> was a Prieſt-taker. <hi>And further ſaith not at preſent.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jurat. Die, &amp; Anno ſupradict. coram me <hi>Edm. Warcup.</hi>
                              </signed>
                              <signed>Jane Bradley.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <p>The ſaid <hi>Jane Bradley</hi> doth further ſay upon her Oath, that the laſt time ſhe ſpoke to the ſaid <hi>Thomas Curtice,</hi> which was when he fetcht a ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat from <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſhe ſaid unto him words to this effect: <hi>When is it that we muſt get the</hi> 5000 <abbr>l</abbr>? <hi>to which he anſwered:</hi> I will not meddle in it; it troubles my conſcience, and it were but treachery in me if it were done, and it is to no purpoſe, to meddle in it, for there is a Liſt found out, or to that effect.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jurat. Die, &amp; Anno ſupradict. coram me <hi>Edm. Warcup.</hi>
                              </signed>
                              <signed>Jane Bradley.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sunday,</hi> November 2. 1679. <hi>At the Council-Board.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>John Gadbury</hi> being examined, ſaith, he hath ſeen <hi>VVilloughby once or twice</hi> at his Houſe with Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and that he believes he may have <hi>caſt his Nativity,</hi> by the name of <hi>Thomas,</hi> at the deſire of Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and two more Nativities for her two Daughters. He ſays, that looking upon <hi>VVilloughby's Horoſcope,</hi> it prognoſticates <hi>a bold and adventurous man;</hi> but does not remember, that he ſaid to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> that <hi>he would be hang'd;</hi> but it's <hi>poſſible he might.</hi> That he caſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Lord Powis</hi>'s Nativity, as he doth that of all Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the certain time of whoſe Birth he can be aſſured of.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:53111:31"/>2. <hi>Matthew Hopkinſon</hi> a Scrivener over againſt <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, that he tranſcribed <hi>a Liſt of Names,</hi> and a Letter of Mr. <hi>VVilloughby's,</hi> in a Room, two pair of ſtairs high; but he does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that it was out of a <hi>womans hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the List, and Letter being ſhewed to him, he owned them to be his hand-writing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Sir <hi>James Buttler,</hi> owned the taking of an <hi>Affidavit,</hi> of <hi>Lane,</hi> about <hi>Buggery</hi> charg'd upon <hi>Mr. Oates,</hi> and that a woman came with the ſaid <hi>Lane</hi> to him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Thomas Jolly</hi> the Taylor, being ſworn, ſays, he carried a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to the <hi>Lady Powis,</hi> and brought back an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Mr. VVilloughby being then preſent.</hi> That he hath ſeen <hi>Mr. VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> half a dozen times at Mrs. <hi>Celliers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the full hearing of theſe ſeveral Informations and Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, we have this publick account of the reſult of the Council.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhite-Hall,</hi> November 2. Mr. <hi>Thomas Dangerfield,</hi> aliàs <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby,</hi> having been examined the 27<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> paſt by the Lords of His Majeſtie's Privy-Council, concerning certain dangerous and treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Papers, ſeiſed in Colonel <hi>Roderick Manſel</hi>'s Chamber, which it appeared to their Lordſhips, had been by him conveyed thither, was therupon by Order of the Board, committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and having ſince given in an Information, to the <hi>Lord Mayor of London,</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral treaſonable practiſes againſt His Majeſtie's Perſon, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and of his having been prevailed with by ſeveral of the Popiſh Religion to counterfeit the above-mentioned Papers and Letters, by which divers Noblemen, and other Proteſtants were to have been brought under a ſuſpicion of carrying on a Plot, againſt His Majeſtie's Government. And the ſaid Information being yeſterday morning brought to His Majeſty by the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> and by <hi>His Majesty</hi> ſent to the <hi>Council-Board,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was ſent for, and further examined by their Lordſhips; who thereupon the laſt Night, committed the Earl of <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to <hi>Newgate;</hi> and did this day likewiſe commit Mr. <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> to the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rigaut</hi> to <hi>Newgate,</hi> ſeveral other Perſons accuſed, being in the Cuſtody of His Majeſtie's Meſſengers; and their Lordſhips have appointed the further Examination of this Matter on Tueſday next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:53111:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Novemb. the</hi> 2d. the ſame day.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <head>1. The Depoſition of <hi>William Woodman,</hi> taken upon Oath on the 2d. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1679. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords of His Majeſties <hi>Moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Council.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>Who ſaith, That he hath known Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> at the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> his Houſe, for about Two Moneths time, and that he hath ſeen him and Mrs. <hi>Cellier, write there very often.</hi> That he carried a Packet of Letters from Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> or Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> at the Tower, and that her Ladyſhip opened the Packet, and read ſome of the Letters, and gave others to him the ſaid <hi>Woodman,</hi> who carried them to one <hi>Nevile,</hi> in the Kings-Bench, and that he hath carried Letters divers times between Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> and <hi>Nevile.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>William Woodman.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <head>2. The Information of <hi>Mary Ayray,</hi> taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, the 2d. day of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1679. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords of His Majeſties <hi>Moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Council.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>This Informant ſaith upon her Oath, <hi>That ſhe went with Willoughby</hi> and <hi>Duddell</hi> to <hi>Nevile</hi> in the Kings-Bench, and left <hi>Willoughby</hi> at a Coffee-houſe by the way, and carried a Sheet of Notes taken at <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Tryal, which <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> writ, but was given her by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> to carry to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile:</hi> And ſhe ſaith ſhe carried a Letter from <hi>Nevile</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and a Letter from Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to the Lady <hi>Powis;</hi> ſhe has alſo ſeen <hi>Singe,</hi> with Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and ſhe has ſeen <hi>Willoughby</hi> write the Speeches of the Five Jeſuites, the which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> did dictate to him: And ſaith alſo, That ſhe has ſeen <hi>Lane</hi> at <hi>Powis</hi>-Houſe, who went by the name of <hi>Johnſon;</hi> and that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ordered him to be called by that Name. This <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53111:32"/>Informant alſo ſaith that ſhe went with my Lady <hi>Abergaveny</hi> laſt Winter, to the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> about her being In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted as a <hi>Popiſh Recuſant,</hi> but has not been at any other time ſince with the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury;</hi> but knows nothing of the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury</hi>'s being threatned to be killed by the Lady <hi>Abergaveny:</hi> And ſaith, That Mr. <hi>Nevile</hi> did bid her tell my Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> that he would write to his Friend.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Mary Ayray.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <head>3. The Information of <hi>Bennett Duddell</hi> a Joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Taken</hi> upon Oath before His <hi>Majeſty in Council: Nov.</hi> 2. 1679.</head>
                           <p>The Informant ſaith, That he hath wrought at <hi>Powis</hi> Houſe, and hath there ſeen Mr. <hi>Willoughby;</hi> that he went with Mrs. <hi>Ayray,</hi> to ſee one in Priſon, in the Kings-Bench, but knew not that his Name was <hi>Nevile,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſtayed in the mean time at a Coffee-houſe thereby. He ſaith, that when they returned, they brought ſome Papers with them, and that ſoon after Mrs. <hi>Ayray</hi> went to the Tower. That he hath at <hi>Powis</hi> Houſe ſeen Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and others often Writing: He remembers that one Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> lay there in the Houſe, and that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> was once in great fear, when ſhe thought that <hi>Lane</hi> was loſt. He doth remember that Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> did once ask him, if he could make a Hand-Preſs, in order to Printing, and he made anſwer, he would ask the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> and his <hi>Lady,</hi> if he might make ſuch a thing: He ſays he went Once or Twice, with Mrs. <hi>Ayray</hi> to the <hi>Gatehouſe;</hi> who went with money to the Priſoners: But the reaſon of his being the more with Mrs. <hi>Ayray,</hi> was by the reaſon of a Match propoſed by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> between him and her: That in <hi>Powis</hi> Houſe there is a private place made by him, and by the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> Order: Sworn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King in Council.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Bennett Duddell.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53111:32"/>
               <head>Tueſday <hi>Novemb,</hi> 4th. 1679.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>His</hi> Majeſty ſate in Council, <hi>in the Afternoon, to Examine further into the Diſcovery made by</hi> Thomas Dangerfield, <hi>alias</hi> Willoughby.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lady</hi> Powis <hi>was called in, to whom the Depoſition of</hi> Woodman <hi>being read, her</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip <hi>ſaid:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That to her knowledge <hi>ſhe never had Packet from</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby, or ever <hi>ſent a Packet to</hi> Nevile: That ſhe has had ſeveral Letters from Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and perhaps ſhe may have given at ſometime a Packet to her Ladyſhips Boy, written from <hi>ſome body elſe.</hi> That her Ladyſhip never went to ſee <hi>Nevile</hi> at the Kings-Bench, but going thither to ſee the Lady <hi>Gage,</hi> ſome body pointed to <hi>Nevile</hi> as he was at the Window, and once before that ſhe thinks ſhe ſaw him elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: That ſhe never had Letter from <hi>Nevile,</hi> though perhaps ſhe might have had one from <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To the Depoſition of</hi> Duddell, <hi>ſhe ſaith:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it is true, one Mr. <hi>Ayray</hi> did bring to the Tower ſome Remarks upon <hi>Langborn</hi>'s Trials; but ſhe never ſaw any thing brought from <hi>Nevile</hi> at the Kings-Bench.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To the Depoſition of</hi> Suſan Edwards, <hi>ſhe ſaith:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That though ſhe had been at Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> ſhe never had once allighted out of her Coach to have Diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>To the Depoſition of Mrs.</hi> Ayray, <hi>ſhe ſaith (as before)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſhe never brought her Ladyſhip any Meſſage from Mr. <hi>Nevile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53111:33"/>5. <hi>To the Depoſition of</hi> Jolly a Taylor, <hi>her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip ſays:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſhe had <hi>Two or Three ſhort Notes</hi> from Mr. <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> as alſo <hi>a great Packet of Papers brought by</hi> Jolly <hi>from him,</hi> but looking them over, ſhe found them very <hi>Inſignificant things;</hi> that once or twice ſhe had ſome ſhort Notes from <hi>Willoughby,</hi> but was much ſurpriſed to receive them.</p>
               <p>She affirms, That <hi>Willoughby</hi> never told her of <hi>his having been alone with the King;</hi> though <hi>ſhe was indeed told it</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Cellier:</hi> But for any ſuch anſwer, as to lament that he was not then prepared to kill the King: She never gave it, and abhors any ſuch thoughts, having <hi>never heard of any ſuch thing,</hi> or <hi>any other Treaſon in her life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That for <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s Lodging ſo long at her Houſe, all the Servants are able to teſtifie, that it was without her knowledge, and when ſhe came there, he ſtill endeavoured to keep out of her ſight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſaid, That after he was Taken, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> went to her Ladyſhip to the Tower, to frame an execuſe touching 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> that ſhould have been lent him by one of her Ladyſhips Servants.</p>
               <p>Her Ladyſhip anſwered, It's true; Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> came to her about ſome contrivance of a Story about 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> to be owing to one of her Servants, but her Ladyſhip chid her ſeverely, and told her ſhe would keep no Servant that could be guilty of ſuch a thing. Her Ladyſhip added, <hi>That ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw</hi> Willoughby <hi>but Twice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> being call'd in, and askt, Whether ſhe had not been at the Tower with the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> to frame ſome excuſe againſt <hi>Willoughby?</hi> She flatly denied the ſame; but being told that the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> had even newly owned it: She then confeſt, That on <hi>Thurſday</hi> Seven-night, ſhe was there, and told her Ladyſhip how <hi>her Husband, and her <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53111:33"/>Son, were bound for</hi> Willoughby<hi>'s appearance,</hi> when <hi>Juſtice Warcup</hi> came, and took him from her Houſe.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Willoughby</hi> did indeed adviſe her to ſay ſomething touching Money due to a Servant of the Lady <hi>Powis;</hi> but that her Ladyſhip hearing thereof, was diſpleaſed at it: Then ſhe railes at <hi>Willoughby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And being told of her Induſtry <hi>to get</hi> Willoughby<hi>'s Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity Caſt:</hi> She ſaid that <hi>Willoughby</hi> having deſired the ſame, ſhe got Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> to do it: But Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ſent her Maid <hi>Margaret,</hi> whileſt he was in Priſon, for <hi>the time of his Birth;</hi> and that he did not underſtand for what intent it was.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Edward Bedford,</hi> was then called in, who referred himſelf to the Account he had given of his Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> by Information to Mr. <hi>Juſtice Warcup.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And further ſaith, That he went about with Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> to ſeveral Clubs.</p>
               <p>That he went with him alſo to <hi>Thompſon in Fetter-Lane,</hi> who was then Printing the <hi>Presbyterian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmaskt:</hi> That Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> has brought with him to the Coffee-Houſe, Papers freſh, and wet from the Preſs: That Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> went to pay Moneys to Mr. <hi>Dormer</hi> in St. <hi>John</hi>'s: That Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> enquired of him after Clubs; and that he name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings-head Club, thither they went, and would have got a Liſt of the Names, but the Drawer refuſed. The like happened at another place; but at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> they got a liſt of about 60. Names of ſuch as uſed to meet there.</p>
               <p>Afterwards they went to the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Ship Taverns,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire if the <hi>D. of Monmouth</hi> had not been there the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Willoughby</hi> told him, How by <hi>Gadbury's</hi> means he was acquainted with Sir <hi>R. Peyton,</hi> and by him was getting
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53111:34"/>into the <hi>Kings-Head Club,</hi> but that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> diſſwaded him upon the account of the Charge, for that they did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make a Purſe of One or Two Guinies a Man, <hi>about ſpecial ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> lay for a time at the Goat near <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>-Houſe, and that going with him once thence to drink <hi>Cock-Ale,</hi> it ſo flew up into <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s head, that going to a <hi>Coffee-houſe,</hi> he raiſed a great Quarrel there, about a word relating to Sir <hi>Thomas Player;</hi> the matter of which had been heard by Mr. <hi>Secretary Coventry.</hi> That <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſhew'd him a Paper call'd <hi>the State of the Three Kingdoms; that</hi> Willoughby <hi>told him, that the</hi> Lord Shaftsbury, <hi>Dr.</hi> Tongue, Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> &amp;c. had private meetings about <hi>Fox-Hall</hi> about the Plot, and that it was there hatched by them: That <hi>Willoughby</hi> had Lodgings at Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> and lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed once unto him his wanting of 20 <abbr>l.</abbr> for ſome great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. That he had been at the Lord <hi>Clarendon</hi>'s, whom Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> complained of as a <hi>dilatory man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> asked <hi>Bedford,</hi> If at their being together in <hi>Cliffords Inn</hi> Garden, he did not receive from him a gift of 40. <abbr>s.</abbr> And if he did not diſcourſe to him <hi>ſo, and ſo,</hi> Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>D. of York,</hi> and of the <hi>D. of Lauderdale,</hi> and about <hi>Scotland?</hi> And touching 300 Horſe that were to be raiſed by Sir <hi>William Waller?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bedford</hi> denies any Gift of 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> in the Garden, but that he borrowed 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> from him at two other times. That he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake to him of either of theſe <hi>Dukes,</hi> or of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And as to the 300 <hi>Horſe,</hi> he has given an Account of that Matter to a Miniſter of State.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> replied, That as to this of the 300 Horſe, he ſpoke it alſo to Mr. <hi>Stanford,</hi> the <hi>D. of Newburgh's</hi> Agent, who if call'd upon, was able to teſtifie the ſame.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Secretary Coventry</hi> telling <hi>Willoughby,</hi> That he had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed how two thirds of the Names mention'd in his Paper-book, were dictated to him, by the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> which he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain affirming, was ordered to Mark the ſaid Names with a Croſs in the Margin, which accordingly was done by him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:53111:34"/>Mr. <hi>Juſtice Warcup</hi> coming in, acquainted the <hi>Board,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi> and his Son in Law <hi>Blaſden</hi> the Apothecary, did both attend: But that there were yet wanting the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſome of their Servants: Upon which the <hi>Lord Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> directed him to take thoſe Examinations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blaſden</hi> call'd in and Sworn, ſaith, That <hi>Margaret</hi> brought him a Note for <hi>Opium,</hi> to cauſe reſt, but he refuſing to follow that direction, he mixed ſomething that was leſs dangerous, which the Maid afterwards told him was ſo weak, that it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified nothing; and therefore ordered him to mix ſomewhat a great deal ſtronger.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi> being askt about the Paper of the Nativity, ſaith, He read it not himſelf, but that his Daughter read it to him. He remembers only ſomething of Propheſie, or a Mans For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. That there were in it, the words <hi>Horoſcope, Venus, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> &amp;c. That the man ſhould be hang'd the latter end of his life; but he knows no more of it, or of whom it was, but that he burned the Paper, and owns that he is a Roman Catholick and a French Merchant.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Blaſden,</hi> in whoſe Houſe the Paper was read, ſays it ſet forth; How that his adventure ſhould be very various, and that he should come before ſome judge, and be in danger in a Sea-Fight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> asked <hi>Cellier</hi> if he did not remember, when in the preſence of his Wife, He ſaid he was then come from the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> This he denies, and alſo that he heard any Diſcourſe extraordinary between <hi>Willoughby</hi> and <hi>Rigaut;</hi> but that <hi>Rigaut</hi> had ſupped twice at his Houſe, and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> and he played at ſome Game together. He denies alſo, That he ſaw any Dagger in his Houſe, or that ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was hid under his Beds-ſide. He acknowledgeth to have ſeen the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> at his Houſe, but not ſix times.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Blaſden</hi> ſays, He has ſeen her Ladyſhips Coach a <hi>dozen times,</hi> which he can ſee plain from his Shop; but does not remember to have ſeen her Ladyſhip go into Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s above twice.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>P.</hi> is call'd in, and having been told what was objected againſt him, as having encouraged Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:53111:35"/>at <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Houſe, <hi>to go again to the</hi> Lord Shaftsbury, <hi>and to be ſure to diſpatch him the third time:</hi> His Lordſhip flatly denies any ſuch thing, and then in a large diſcourſe, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to the known Method of his Life and Converſation, his conſtant Services to the Crown, and how little he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in this matter, as being known by <hi>all good Men</hi> not to be capable of ſuch a thing: That as to the <hi>Earl of Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> he came lately over with great expectation of his aid and favour in Parliament, touching an unhappy difference ariſen with <hi>a great Ally</hi> (meaning his Son-in-Law's Father) and that the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> had already teſtified ſo much Countenance in this matter, that he came over full of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to do that Lord greater Services than he can well expreſs.</p>
               <p>That before his Daughter was diſpoſed of in Marriage, then a very Noble Lady, <hi>The Lady Powis,</hi> who had teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied very great Inclinations, to have her married to her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhips Nephew: Upon which Obligation, he then grew Intimate with the ſaid Lady; and being a perſon that is not wont to forget his friends in their afflictions, had often gone to that Lady to give her the beſt Comfort he could. That waiting on her Ladyſhip, when he came lately from <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſhe recommended to him <hi>juſt at parting,</hi> a very charitable Woman, one Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> unto whom the <hi>late Dutcheſs</hi> of <hi>York</hi> was a Debtor in 5 or 600 <abbr>l.</abbr> That his Lordſhip being one of the Duke's Commiſſioners, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to further her buſineſs: That in further recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Woman, the Lady added, That ſhe was a great Servant to the Duke, and alſo to the King: and alſo being a Woman of great Underſtanding, and getting acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by her opportunity of being a Midwife, into many conſiderable Families, ſhe had wrought about ſeveral incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Perſons to be of better Principles and Inclinations, both to the King, and the Duke; and more particularly, That this Woman had now found out <hi>a man,</hi> who was very able to diſcover very dangerous practices againſt the King.</p>
               <p>That Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> came ſoon after to his Lodgings, That ſhe gave a great Character of one <hi>Willoughby,</hi> who had much improved himſelf abroad in the Service of the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> and under the <hi>D. de Villa Hermoſa;</hi> That this man <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53111:35"/>coming over, and reſorting to the <hi>Coffee-houſes,</hi> was much ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, at the Rebellious diſcourſes, that he heard, but that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing his thoughts, he grew familiar with the moſt mutinous, who liked him ſo well, that they carried him to their Clubs and private meetings, and being admitted to their ſecrets, he found, that great and dangerous things were preparing againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
               <p>That ſhe deſired his Lordſhip but to procure a Warrant for making a ſearch, and that all the whole matter would be plainly diſcovered, but ſhe deſir'd, that this Warrant might be obtain'd without the Kings knowledge. That of all this Information his Lordſhip gave an account to the Duke, who refuſing to have any thing acted therein without the Kings knowledge, <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> came with Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to his Lodgings, where the Duke ſaw him, and he was afterwards handed to the King.</p>
               <p>That when <hi>VVilloughby</hi> came afterwards to his Lordſhip, he mention'd the difficulty of getting a Warrant, and complaining of want of Zeal in the Kings Miniſters, he ſaid he would yet do his buſineſs <hi>without a VVarrant, and by the Cuſtome-houſe way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That as concerning the <hi>Lord Shaftsbury, Willoughby</hi> told him that there was ſome woman about the Duke, that Writ to the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> all the dangerous things ſhe could invent, and to make proof of this, came afterwards to ſhew two Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which his Lordſhip preſently ſaw were Written in Sir <hi>Rich. Bulſtrodes</hi> hand, and contained nothing touching the Duke, but ſuch matters of common intelligence from <hi>Bruxells,</hi> as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or any other man might fitly write.</p>
               <p>Whereupon <hi>Willoughby</hi> pretended to him, that there was a third Letter of greater importance, which he had loſt, but as to thoſe two Letters his Lordſhip ſays they were given to the King.</p>
               <p>Soon after this, <hi>Willoughby</hi> came to him, at midnight, and ſaid, he was going to Priſon, to which his Lordſhip could only ſay, that if he were guilty of any harm, he knew not how to help him, but if he were to ſuffer by miſtake, the Kings Miniſters would ſoon diſcover it, and ſet him again at liberty.</p>
               <p>His Lordſhip upon <hi>Willinghbies</hi> Queſtion, did own that he being at Dinner at <hi>Lambs, Willoughby</hi> did there come to him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a meeting to be had at Mr. <hi>Gadburies</hi> with Sir <hi>Robert Peyton,</hi> and perhaps it might be upon a Letter from the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> as <hi>Willoughby</hi> affirms.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53111:36"/>His <hi>Lordſhip</hi> doth acknowledge, that he gave his Servants charge to admit <hi>Willoughby,</hi> when ever he came: and that he did alſo call him <hi>Captain Willoughby:</hi> but the occaſion was, that he telling his Lordſhip, that he hoped His <hi>Majeſty</hi> would gratifie him, and provide him as good an employment, as he had refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the otherſide, his Lordſhip did ſay, Doubtleſs His <hi>Majeſty</hi> would provide for him, and that when ever any forces were ſent abroad, he need not fear but that he ſhould have a Company.</p>
               <p>That he did not wonder at all at <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s confident words, ſince they have been the beſt Cards he had to Play for his Life: but that his Lordſhips actions in the World have been ſuch, as will exempt him from any ſhadow of reflection that can happen by ſuch a Creature as this.</p>
               <p>As to the buſineſs of Sir <hi>R. Peyton,</hi> he would conceal nothing that the Council deſired to know. And firſt, he ſays, that he knows not that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was privy to any thing relating to <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby;</hi> but that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> telling him, (as he ſaid before) the good offices ſhe had done the King, and Duke, with ſome that were inflamed againſt him, ſhe named Sir <hi>Robert Peyton</hi> for one, who told her, that if he could be forgiven what was paſt, he would come in, and help the Government, but his greateſt fear was from the Duke, who was thought to be a perſon of Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that could not forgive: That when his Lordſhip aſſured Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> of the contrary; ſhe told him, that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> would not be willing to meet at any publick place, but at Mr. <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries</hi> he would. Where accordingly they met; where Sir <hi>Robert Peyton</hi> declared he would come in to the Kings ſervice <hi>to all pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes;</hi> that he ſeem'd to complain of ſome hard meaſure, and doubted much of the Dukes reconciliation: but his Lordſhip going far towards Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> ſatisfaction, he afterwards met the Duke at his Lordſhips Lodgings, and had all the aſſurance he could deſire; which is all that he knows, or could ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sir <hi>Robert Peyton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> does acknowledge, that he told his Lordſhip of an ill woman in the Dukes Family, that correſponded with the <hi>Lord Shaftsbury,</hi> and that, he ſaid, he had loſt one of the Letters.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Lordſhip</hi> tells the <hi>Board,</hi> that he cannot but be troubled to have his name mention'd by ſo infamous a perſon as this was, but yet, if any whoever ſhould come to morrow to him again, &amp; tell
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53111:36"/>him of any dangerous practiſes againſt the King and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> or any other Lord whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, he ſhould hold himſelf bound in duty to hearken to any ſuch perſon, and to endavour to diſcover ſuch danger by all the ways he could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Lordſhip being withdraws: Willoughby</hi> added, that <hi>the two Letters</hi> mention'd were by him found in a drawer at the Lord <hi>Shaftsburies.</hi> That he gave them to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> complaining they were Writ in an ill hand, but ſhe carried them to the <hi>Tower,</hi> ſaying the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> could read <hi>any hand.</hi> And further ſays, that althô the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> found upon peruſal of them that they were of no importance, <hi>yet becauſe they might teſtifie</hi> that he was admitted to privacy with the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> they thought fit he ſhould make uſe of them, in the manner he did:</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>John Webb of Miſſenden in the County of Bucks,</hi> being call'd in ſays. He knows Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> but remembers not when he went down to his houſe, but that he was ſent by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> not by the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> that he knows nothing of any Letters ſent down by him, or of one Mrs. <hi>Jean,</hi> or any other Prieſt at his houſe: that he onely went down to fetch up a Child.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> obejects, that he knows <hi>Jean</hi> ſo well, that at his laſt coming from home, he brought him a Letter from <hi>Jean,</hi> being then at Mrs. <hi>Celliers, Webb</hi> denying this, the very Letter found by Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> is produced, and read, upon which Mr. <hi>Webb</hi> ſaid, <hi>it was poſſible, but he had forgot it.</hi> And <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſaying, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> was by, when that Letter was deliver'd to him, <hi>Cellier</hi> denied it, but <hi>Willoughby</hi> replyed that <hi>VVebb</hi> knew all, as well as what he would now excuſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Copy of the aforeſaid Letter from <hi>H. Jean</hi> to Mr. <hi>VVilloughby.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Received yours on <hi>Monday</hi> laſt, and think my ſelf much obliged to you, for that you remember your Captive Friend It is ſome divertiſment to my retired Life to hear ſometimes how affairs ſtand, both that I may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter know how to ſet my steps that are laid for Innocent men <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53111:37"/>and learn alſo how to value an innocent ſolitude more than the tumults of a confuſed VVorld. I perceive by yours, the old Sticklers are ſtill buſie, and ſtrive <hi>to blind the peoples Eyes with a Popiſh Plot, that their own may not be ſeen; when was there ever Miſchief or Treaſon hatcht againſt Monarchy, but under the Cloak of Religion, and Zeal againſt Popery?</hi> Things are ſo plain that who is not wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blind, must needs ſee <hi>the good Old Cauſe,</hi> taking Life again: God bleſs the King, and direct his Council. That we may live in Peace, and Juſtice under him. This is the Prayer of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your very humble Servant, <hi>H. JEAN.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Octob. 1ſt. 1679.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Pray preſent my humble Service to <hi>Mounſieur Cellier,</hi> and his <hi>Lady.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Porter</hi> Butler to the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> being ſworn ſays, that he is a Proteſtant. That he has ſeen <hi>Willoughby</hi> at <hi>Powis houſe</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, and that he lodged there, but not by the knowledge of the Lord, or Lady, as the <hi>Porter</hi> told him: he remembers that <hi>Lane</hi> was alſo there by the name of <hi>Johnſon:</hi> he does confeſs he gave <hi>VVilloughby</hi> a bottle of <hi>Sherry,</hi> at the <hi>Tower,</hi> but not by the Lords order: and that <hi>VVilloughby,</hi> dined there another day: and that he did lead <hi>VVilloughby</hi> to the Lodgings of the Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Bellaſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Lane,</hi> being call'd in, ſays, that he lay at <hi>Powis houſe,</hi> for a Moneth or ſix Weeks, by order of <hi>VVilloughby,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> from whom he had his Diet. That he went by the name of <hi>Johnſon,</hi> fearing to be arreſted by Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> for what he had teſtified againſt him, and in that fear he went down to <hi>Grayes,</hi> near <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and had a pair of Shoes given him by <hi>VVilloughby,</hi> who alſo got him out of Priſon, which was a chargeable work. He ſays, he made an <hi>Affidavit</hi> before Sir <hi>James Butler.</hi> And being ask't by <hi>one of the Lords,</hi> whether he had not <hi>before the Houſe of Lords,</hi> made two contrary <hi>Affidavits,</hi> he acknowledged that out of fear he did ſo: but that the firſt <pb n="65" facs="tcp:53111:37"/>drawn by <hi>Willoughby,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Nevil</hi> had directed was true, and the other falſe.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> being call'd in, ſays he knows <hi>Willoughby,</hi> when he met at <hi>Powis houſe,</hi> going there in ſearch of <hi>Lane,</hi> who was to give Evidence for him; that the Examinant knowing in whoſe houſe he had been, was much troubled, inaſmuch as he is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. It is true, that he being in Priſon, Writ little Notes to his Brother, under the door, but knows not who conveyed them. That he knows Mrs. <hi>Ayry</hi> that he has ſeen Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> at Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> houſe, and there has had ſome money of him, though he was ever Cautious of him, fearing he was a Papiſt. That he met him once at <hi>Procters</hi> Coffe houſe, where an <hi>Affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit</hi> made by <hi>Osborn</hi> was read unto him, and owns that <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> did deliver Papers to him. He alſo owns that <hi>Rogers,</hi> and <hi>Shereman</hi> the Sadler did tell him, that they heard <hi>Nevil</hi> report how he had furniſht money to get the Examinant out of Priſon; which he with anger queſtioning <hi>Nevil</hi> about, <hi>Nevil</hi> made anſwer it was true, and plain demonſtration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Dormer</hi> being call'd in, ſays, he knows <hi>Mr. Willoughby,</hi> having ſeen him at Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> from whom <hi>Willoughby</hi> once brought him five pound. And that he had ſeen Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> twice or thrice at <hi>Powis houſe,</hi> where he has been to wait upon the Lady, to whom he is related: and that he has been at Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> to ſee a Child brought from <hi>Peterley,</hi> that is his <hi>Nephew.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Web</hi> of <hi>Peterly</hi> is his Kinſman, that he knows not of Mr. <hi>Jean</hi> nor any ſuch man there: having not been for theſe three quarters of a year at that houſe. That he knowns nothing at all <hi>of any ground of the Presbyterian Plot</hi> mentioned by <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> and ſays he never carried to the <hi>Tower,</hi> the Pamphlet call'd <hi>Traytors transform'd into Martyrs;</hi> but that indeed, he had one of thoſe books, and remembers he gave it to Mrs <hi>Cellier,</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her once with <hi>Willoughby</hi> in <hi>Tower-ſtreet.</hi> He owns that he ſaw <hi>Willoughby</hi> once at the <hi>Rainbow Coffe Houſe,</hi> and there pull'd of his Hat without ſpeaking to him, that he has ſeen the <hi>Danby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi> but knows not who Writ them.</p>
               <p>Being askt if he heard any thing of the murther of the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> he ſaid that ſeveral Moneths ago, there was ſuch a report, and that one <hi>Adamſon</hi> a Watch-maker, with a Barber, and others in <hi>Holborn</hi> were concern'd in it: but that he never heard any thing elſe thereof, much leſs ever conſulted ſuch a thing with the Lady <hi>Abergaveney:</hi> that he knows <hi>Turner</hi> the Bookſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53111:38"/>and had the Pamphlet aforementioned from him, but denies that ever he Writ the ſame, or that he ever delivered five pounds to one <hi>Sharp</hi> to pray for any mans Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mrs. Woodman</hi> who lives in <hi>Drury-Lane;</hi> at the Corner houſe of <hi>parkers-Lane,</hi> being call'd in, ſaith, that <hi>Margaret</hi> formerly Maid to Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> had been without attending, but would be gone, thô ſhe adviſed her to ſtay, and that being out of Service ſhe knows not where to find her.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> bid her tell <hi>Margaret,</hi> (if they meet) that a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſhall take her in Cuſtody, unleſs ſhe attends the Clerk of the Council of her own accord.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <head>Middleſex and Westminſter.</head>
                           <head>The Information of <hi>Thomas Curtis</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Clothworker, taken this 5th. day of <hi>November</hi> 1679. before me <hi>Edward Warcup</hi> 
                              <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace in the ſaid County and City.</head>
                           <p>This Informant ſaith, that about half a year ago, he became acquainted with Mr. <hi>Thomas Willoughby,</hi> taking him to be a very civil Gentleman, and not knowing that he had any other name: and about the ſecond day of <hi>October</hi> laſt, he met the ſaid <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> at the <hi>Hoop Tavern</hi> on <hi>Fiſh ſtreet Hill,</hi> and there drank a Bottle of Rheniſh Wine with him, in the drinking whereof the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> told this Informant that he looked on him as an honeſt man, and one that loved his King and Country, and expreſs'd himſelf to be a Proteſtant, and much againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; and he further added, that he would put this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant into a way to ſerve his King and Country, whereunto this Informant replyed, that he would ſerve his King and Country to the laſt drop of his Blood in any thing that is juſt; to which the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> replied, he would not put this Informant, on any thing but what was honourable and juſt, and he would make it eaſie: but at that time he refuſed to tell the buſineſs, but appointed this Informant to Dine with him at Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> on the next day following, which this Informant did, and after Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> took this Informant into a private room above, and there told this Informant, that there were Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons giving out privately by the Phanaticks, and perſwaded this Informant to get one, and if this Informant did ſo, he would bring this Informant to the King, and that it ſhould be 5000 <abbr>l.</abbr> in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants <pb n="67" facs="tcp:53111:38"/>way, beſides being taking care of for the future, but this Informant replying, he did not believe there was any ſuch thing, the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> anſwered, he knew it to be true, and that he had been at ſeveral meetings with them, and named one in <hi>Holborne,</hi> another which he called Sir <hi>Thomas Players,</hi> or my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s in <hi>London,</hi> a third that was Sir <hi>Robert Peytons,</hi> and he particularly ſaid that <hi>Bloods</hi> party iſſued out theſe Commiſſions; and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant had heard before, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> had harboured the Gentlemen, that came over from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and that ſhe was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, but the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> did never intimate to this Informant that he vvas employed by the Papiſts in this affair, and he charged this Informant not to ſay any thing of this matter to Mr. <hi>Nevil,</hi> becauſe he had no correſpondence vvith him, nor deſired any, nor to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> becauſe ſhe vvas a vvoman: and then this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant promiſed him to ſee vvhat could be done, and ſo left him, reſolving not to inſinuate into any ſecret truſt on purpoſe to betray it; about four days after vvhich, this Informant return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and told him he had been at the Club in <hi>Weſtminster</hi> Market, but could not learn any ſuch thing, and vvhen this Informant hath not ſeen the ſaid <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and this Informant vvent to Mr. <hi>Nevil,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nevil</hi> bid this Informant never to meddle with ſuch Villanous treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys. And this Informant, further ſaith, that he likevviſe told Mrs. <hi>Jane Bradley</hi> the ſame Story, and that he heard that Mr. <hi>Bloods</hi> Party, the <hi>Phanatiques</hi> had the giving out thoſe Commiſſions, and ſhe then ſaid, ſhe would uſe her intereſt with one Capt. <hi>Brown</hi> (who had formerly been her Sweet-Heart) to get one, and the ſaid <hi>Jane Bradly</hi> hath ſeveral times ſince wiſht we could get the 5000 <abbr>l.</abbr> ſaying ſhe would ſhare therein: And this Informant did tell her, that he heard, thoſe Commiſſions were given out by Mr. <hi>Bloods</hi> Party, by thoſe people where he was concerned, and that this Informant would beg his bread, before he would be guilty of ſuch treacherous deſigns; and that it was to no purpoſe to meddle in it, for there is a liſt found out, as he heard. And this Informant remembers the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> asked this Informant, if he knew Collonel <hi>Manſel,</hi> which this Informant ſaid he did; and he alſo told this Informant, he had been in the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s company or Club, and further ſaith not.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jurat. Die &amp; anno ſupradict. cor. me Edmund Warcup.</signed>
                              <signed>Thomas Curtis.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:53111:39"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="information">
                           <p>This Informant further ſaith that Mrs. <hi>Bradly</hi> asked him, in whoſe name the ſaid Commiſſions were to iſſue out, where unto this Informant anſwerd that he heard that it was in the name of the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of England:</hi> and did further ſay, he heard ſome ſhould hold that <hi>the long Parliament was not yet diſſolved:</hi> But this Informant does not rember from whom he heard theſe particulars.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jurat: codem Die. Edmond Warcup.</signed>
                              <signed>Thomas Curtis.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Fryday</hi> November 7th. 1679. <hi>in the Afternoon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Dangerfeild, <hi>was ſent for, and in his preſence</hi> Margaret Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins <hi>formerly Servant to Mr.</hi> Cellier <hi>being</hi> Sworn and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogated by him, <hi>ſaith,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſhe carried money to him in <hi>New-gate,</hi> but remembers not how much it was, that he was afterwards <hi>in the Counter,</hi> and ſending earneſtly to her Miſtreſs to get him out, ſhe ſent the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant to him with 50 <abbr>s.</abbr> but the ſame not being ſufficient ſhe brought it back again, and 3 <abbr>l.</abbr> was afterwards ſent.</p>
               <p>She acknowledges that her Miſtreſs bid him get out by <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and that being out he ſhould preſently come to her: that ſhe did carry ſeveral letters between him, and her Mrs. but knows not what they were.</p>
               <p>That ſhe did carry two ſmall Vials to the Kings Bench, but knows not what they concerned, nor whether the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> was concern'd in that Advice. That after carrying the firſt Bottle ſhe went next morning to the Kings Bench, and that <hi>Willoughby</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t her for a ſecond Bottle, it being in a little Vial Glaſs.</p>
               <p>She ovvns that he ſpoke to her about ſending to Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> and told her alſo of his acquaintance vvith <hi>Strode,</hi> for that they had formerly been padding together.</p>
               <p>That ſhe once brought money to him to give to <hi>Mounſon:</hi> that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> did acquaint the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> of <hi>Willoughby</hi>'s deſire to ſee <hi>Bedlow,</hi> to vvhich her Ladiſhip anſvver'd. He might do vvhat he pleaſed, for ſhe vvould not meddle vvith that matter. That <hi>Willoughby</hi> told her, he had made <hi>Strode</hi> high in drink, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomething that hindred him from being in the ſame Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and that he gave her ſome Notes of vvhat he had then learned from <hi>Strode.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:53111:39"/>As to the cauſe of her turning away, ſhe ſays it was on this account: An <hi>Iriſh</hi>-man who is a Sollicitor, came once and told her, that her Miſtreſs had got an ill Repute, by keeping <hi>Willoughby for her Stallion.</hi> And that the truth was, they lived in <hi>ſuch a manner together at</hi> Powis-<hi>houſe,</hi> that the old man her Husband was ſent up thither to keep them honeſt. That of this ſhe gave ſome account to Mrs. <hi>Cellier's</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and upon this occaſion ſhe was turned away: her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs alſo telling her, that ſeeing ſhe could not live quietly at her own Houſe, ſhe had no farther need of her Service.</p>
               <p>She ſays, ſhe ſaw <hi>Willoughby</hi> twice at <hi>Powis-Houſe,</hi> the time ſhe was there waiting at the Table on her Miſtreſs and him; and that ſhe poach'd Eggs for them both: being asked whether ſhe did not lately hear from Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> by way of advice and inſtruction how to behave her ſelf, ſhe denied that ſhe had any Letter or Meſſage from her, or had ſeen her of a long time.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Nevil, alias Payne,</hi> is called in, and unto what Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> objects, he ſays he knows <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> and has ſeen him four times at <hi>Powis-houſe.</hi> That he knows not of <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi>'s going to Mr. <hi>Webb</hi>'s in <hi>Buckinghamſhire.</hi> That he never had Letters or Papers from the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> in his life; but that with Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> many Letters and Papers have paſt: and denies not but that the <hi>Danby-Reflections</hi> paſt out of his hands.</p>
               <p>That by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> the Papers of <hi>Knox, Lane,</hi> and <hi>Osborne,</hi> were brought to him for his advice; which having given, he ſent back. He remembers that <hi>Willoughby</hi> did attend <hi>in the Rules,</hi> when Mrs. <hi>Ayry</hi> and <hi>Dowdell</hi> came over to him: but knows nothing of twenty ſeven Papers that he ſhould ſend back; and deſires if any ſuch thing be objected to him, that he may ſee his hand.</p>
               <p>That for the many <hi>Liſts</hi> objected he ſhould ſend over, he denies the ſame. He ſays he knows <hi>Mounſon</hi> and <hi>Kemiſh</hi> from many years acquaintance. He owns that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> came to him in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> to tell him of Tortures uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Prance,</hi> and how that the Lord <hi>Shaftesbury</hi> was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up <hi>Strode</hi> to be a new Witneſs. He ſays <hi>Willoughby</hi> told him, that he had turned <hi>Strode</hi> the wrong ſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:53111:40"/>He denies the ſending of any <hi>Letters,</hi> or <hi>Liſts</hi> to his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; and never any Letter to the <hi>Tower</hi> by any Woman: he knows not of the <hi>Affidavit</hi> made by <hi>Lane,</hi> but will not deny ſuch a thing. He ſays that <hi>Knox</hi> was troubled he ſhould declare as he did, for that he was told, that by the Charity which Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> diſperſed, he was taken from Priſon.</p>
               <p>He ſays that the ſecond diſcourſe he had with <hi>Willoughby</hi> at <hi>Powis-houſe,</hi> was, how that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> had offered to procure him an Enſigns place under the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> in the late Expedition to <hi>Scotland,</hi> or elſe to ſtay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon her.</p>
               <p>He ſays farther, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> from being his Friend, became his utter Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> replies, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> had ſent him 80 <abbr>l.</abbr> and that her Husband had been his Security to keep him from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but that upon ſome difference ariſing, upon complaint made that <hi>Nevils</hi> Daughter was like to turn Whore, <hi>old Cellier</hi> withdrew his Security, and ſo <hi>Nevil</hi> was returned to Priſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nevile</hi> in anſwer to this reviles <hi>Willoughby</hi> with many paſſionate expreſſions; and as to the writing the Pamphlet <hi>Timothy Touchſtone,</hi> he denies it, and ſays he knows nothing of Mr. <hi>Jeane the Prieſt</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to one <hi>Cox</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> he has been his Agent about his buſineſs in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but denies to have heard any thing from him about Ten thouſand pound which Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> does object. He does acknowledge that he was ſtill for the Advice for <hi>Indicting falſe Witneſſes,</hi> and had twenty times adviſed the Indicting <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedloe;</hi> but as for the framing a <hi>Presbyterian Plot,</hi> and to draw Men in it, it had been a great villany, and he utterly denies the ſame.</p>
               <p>That he onely had from Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> Fifteen pound, but that ſhe had of his money Seventeen pound: That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce between her and <hi>Willoughby</hi> was very ſcandalous, and ſhe was ſuſpected to defraud the Charity which came through her hands, which by the collection of all ſorts of Catholicks was about Twenty two pounds <hi>per</hi> week.</p>
               <p>He acknowledges, that he adviſed <hi>Willoughby</hi> to compound his Debts, and not to depend on ſhifts of Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:53111:40"/>He owns that he received all the Tryals that were prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and had fingerd them out, as will ſtill appear by the Books he has by him: for that ſeeing how ill things hung together, and that ſome things look like Perjury, he thought it was eaſie to frame Indictments againſt the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>That as to his informing <hi>Willoughby</hi> of a Liſt of <hi>Mutinous Coffee-houſes,</hi> he denies the ſame, having never been in four or five in his life; but it was notorious enough how all the Coffee-houſes were factious.</p>
               <p>He declares his great hatred and animoſity againſt Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> who formerly indeed came to him every day; but that ſhe cauſed her Husband to withdraw his Bayl, and he was again clapt up.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Dangerfield</hi> objects, That it was not altogether Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> but the advice of the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> that he ſhould be again confined: foraſmuch as when he was formerly in that condition, he had been very induſtrious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout writing of Papers in their buſineſs; but that being at liberty, he chiefly followed the Play-houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nevile</hi> here reflects upon him as a lewd and infamous perſon. To which <hi>Willoughby</hi> replies, <hi>If I were ſuch as you ſay, it makes it the more plain, that I could not proceed in ſuch weighty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings as I have managed, without conſiderable Counſel and Direction; which is agreeable to what I have affirmed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:53111:41"/>
            <head>The Narrator's Concluſion to the whole Work.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <div type="section">
               <p>THe Net muſt be cunningly caſt, that takes all the Fiſh in the River; and this Narrative, though it can mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly mention its own induſtry, yet dares not preſume that nothing has eſcaped its diligence: but beſides, it might ſeem uncivil to leave nothing wherein the Pen of another might travel: to reap the Fields ſo clean, that there ſhould be no gleaning for the Poor, is Cruelty; to leave no Cluſters after the Vintage, would be interpreted Covetouſneſs: and yet I dare avow, that he that complains of Penury in this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, will hardly furniſh out his Table with a more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Treat. But becauſe there are ſome particulars which might have been crowded in before, yet not without Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, which I thought the Reader would grudge if he knew they had eſcaped him, I was willing to adde a few Remarkables, which I rather purpoſely reſerved for this place, than careleſsly omitted in the body of the Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§ 1.</head>
               <p>Then it deſerves a ſpecial Remark, that this Mr. <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> who whilſt he was a ſervant to an Inſtrument in the carrying on their grand Intrigue, was a man of great parts, amongſt them a gallant Gentleman; as ſoon as he begins to be honeſt, to reflect upon thoſe Mazes of Villany wherein by their ſeduction he had trodden, now all of the ſudden hears nothing from them, but an infamous perſon, one of no Credit, whoſe Teſtimony muſt not paſs for any thing. Strange! that he who was thought a credible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to have faſtned a Paramount Treaſon upon ſo many Noble Proteſtant Lords, and worthy Gentlemen, ſhould loſe his Credibility when he comes to recriminate, and caſt the Guilt where it ought to lie, upon a ſmall number of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. 'Tis a ſingular happineſs that our Papiſts have, that their Agents are all honeſt whilſt they do miſchief, and <pb n="103" facs="tcp:53111:41"/>preſently Villains when they diſcover it. Thus they dealt with all thoſe, whom remorſe and a timely reflexion upon their own evil ways, wrought upon to diſcover the late Plot; uſed their Agency, abaſed their ſimplicity to execute their Projects, and then decryed them for debaucht Criminals, when they could ſerve themſelves and their Cauſe no longer of them: from whence we learn, that there's no Crime ſo great amongſt them as Repentance. I will here give the Reader the Minutes of the Examinations before His Majeſty in Council, <hi>Tueſday, November</hi> 4. 1679. relating to this one Remark.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Lady <hi>Powis</hi> ſaith, <hi>She hopes the Oath of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous perſon ſhall not bring her in danger, for that no body of common ſenſe would ever confide any thing of Importance to ſuch a Creature as he:</hi> A very <hi>ingenuous Reflection,</hi> firſt, to make him <hi>infamous,</hi> by his Ghoſtly Fathers <hi>Indulgence to be drunk,</hi> and then to plead his Infamy to cover their own: but let Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> anſwer for himſelf, who gave this ſmart Repartee to her Ladiſhip, <hi>That he was not ſo inconſiderable in their Opinion, but that they were willing to get him out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the charge of Sixty pound, which in all places it coſt him, as may appear by his Book which was taken out of his Cloſet by Sir</hi> Will. Waller.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> to whom Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> was ſuch a Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that they were <hi>hand and glove;</hi> ſhe that uſed to admire his excellent parts, and rare dexterity in the manage of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, yet now ſays, <hi>She never cauſed</hi> Willoughby <hi>or any body elſe to put forth Pamphlets, but that indeed he did make ſome, and put them forth; which were very inconſiderable things. That</hi> Willoughby <hi>did once read to her two Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, wherein was no matter of hurt; but the things were foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and mere</hi> Chimaera's. <hi>Then ſhe rails at, and reviles</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet this good Gentlewoman when ſhe came to introduce Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> to the Right Honourable the E. of <hi>P.</hi> gave a high Character of him, that he had much improved himſelf abroad in the ſervice of the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Lord <hi>P.</hi> called in, ſaith, <hi>That he gave his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants charge to admit</hi> Willoughby <hi>whenever he came, and that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53111:42"/>he did call him Captain</hi> Willoughby; <hi>yet his Lordſhip tells the Board, he cannot but be troubled to have his name mentioned by ſo infamous a perſon as this was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Nevile,</hi> alias <hi>Payne,</hi> called into the Council on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>Nov.</hi> 7. 1679, ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Willoughby <hi>had writ him a kind of a Challenge, which he rejected upon knowledge of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous life; beſides, that he was grown in his behaviour proud, and as high as a Prince. That the Commerce between Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>and</hi> Willoughby, <hi>was very ſcandalous; that ſhe was ſuſpected to defrand the Charity which came through her hands, which by the collection of all ſorts of Catholicks, was about</hi> 22 <abbr>l.</abbr> per <hi>week.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§ 2.</head>
               <p>I muſt apologize for the Non-appearance of the ſo-much-celebrated Liſt of Names fixed or endeavoured to be fixt upon the Lodgings of the Narrator in <hi>Ax-yard,</hi> which I have many cogent Reaſons to conceal. 1. Leſt it ſhould tempt the worthy perſons therein to ſtudy ſome revenge upon the Catholicks, which being ſo inconſiſtent with Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, thoſe gallant Gentlemen will ſatisfie themſelves with their own Innocency, and willingly want what might have awakened even a juſt Indignation. 2. I know not how far <hi>ſuch a Liſt</hi> might provoke any perſon againſt my ſelf: and yet I muſt ſay thus much; I could be content to be half hang'd, to ſave the lives or the longings of ſuch honourable perſons. 3. I have a Reaſon worth two of theſe; I did not, becauſe I could not publiſh it, all my induſtry and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not having been able hitherto to procure it: It was once in my Chamber, it ſeems, when I was willing to be honeſtly rid of it; but now I wiſh it there, it will not come: and I profeſs I will forgive Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> from the beginning of the world to this day, if he will once more come and pin it at my beds-head, and the Key ſhall lie under the door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt he is at leiſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§ 3.</head>
               <p>One particular, omitted in the Information of Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield,</hi> muſt here be retrieved. The next day (ſays he) I went to Lord <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> who demanded, <hi>Why I was ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53111:42"/>willing to do that for which I was taken out of the Priſon?</hi> and frown'd much on me, and ſent his man down; and I fearing his fury, laid my hand to my Sword, and came down ſtairs, he not approaching, and went away, and told Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> my Lord <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> was angry with me: <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>'tis his cuſtom to fall out one hour, and be good friends the next.</hi> Then ſhe adviſed me to <hi>go to Confeſſion and Receive;</hi> which I did of Mr. <hi>Sharp;</hi> and he having notice of my Refuſal to my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> and Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> would ſcarce let me come from him, but told me, <hi>I muſt do Penance, for denying to ſerve God in that which the Scriptures taught:</hi> Then I demanded, <hi>If they taught me to kill my King?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Yes, if he were condemned thereby.</hi> But I got from him, and was then about to have diſcovered all: But coming home, I found the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> with Mrs. <hi>Cellier;</hi> and when ſhe ſaw me, ſent for me in, and laughed. I ſaid, <hi>Madam, it is not a laughing matter I</hi> Then ſhe ſaid, <hi>Know you what I laugh at?</hi> I anſwered, <hi>I did. Well, well,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>Mr.</hi> Willoughby <hi>will be honeſt, and do us no harm, I am ſure.</hi> Then I ſat down, and had ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and ſhe ſaid, <hi>The Duke of</hi> York <hi>was coming, and that would ſomewhat qualifie the Rage of the Presbyterians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What theſe Romiſh Zealots will be at next, time muſt diſcover; and when time ſhall diſcover it, I wiſh the Proteſtants may make a good improvement of their Mercies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
